<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Susanna's apologie against the elders. Or A vindication of Susanna Parr; one of those two women lately excommunicated by Mr Lewis Stycley, and his church in Exeter. / Composed and published by her selfe, for the clearing of her own innocency, and the satisfaction of all others, who desire to know the true reason of their so rigorous proceedings against her.</title>
            <author>Parr, Susanna.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1784_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209665</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868530</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868530</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170370</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91478)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170370)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 223:E1784[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Susanna's apologie against the elders. Or A vindication of Susanna Parr; one of those two women lately excommunicated by Mr Lewis Stycley, and his church in Exeter. / Composed and published by her selfe, for the clearing of her own innocency, and the satisfaction of all others, who desire to know the true reason of their so rigorous proceedings against her.</title>
                  <author>Parr, Susanna.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 114 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Henry Hall for T. Robinson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year, 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "may: May. 12.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Parr, Susanna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Stycley, Lewis, 1621-1687 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Excommunication --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170370:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SVSANNA'S Apologie againſt the ELDERS.</p>
            <p>OR A Vindication of SVSANNA PARR; one of thoſe two Women lately <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> LEWIS STVCLEY, and his Church in <hi>Exeter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compoſed and Publiſhed by her ſelfe, for the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of her own Innocency, and the Satisfaction of all others, who deſire to know the true Reaſon of their ſo rigorous Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt her.</p>
            <q>Whoſe hatred is covered by deceit, his wickedneſſe ſhall be ſhewed before the whole Congregation. <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 26.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>They ſhall put you out of the Synagogues, yea the time cometh, that whoſoever killeth you will think that he doth God ſervice. <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 16.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Let us go forth therefore unto him without the Campe, bearing his reproach, <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 13.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170370:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170370:2"/>
            <head>To the Impartiall READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a thorny path, and a myrie way that I am compelled to walke in; a way wherein there is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of looſing more in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, rather then of regaining what is already loſt. A way, the walking wherein, all the comfort I have, is the hope of getting out of it at laſt, and ſo it concerns me to haſten as faſt as I can. In it I meet with the Enemies Sword, covered over with zeale for God and his glory, when as nothing of this hath appeared in the leaſt, either in the worke, or in the managing thereof: Satan is now tranſformed into an Angel of light, But my hope is, that he will in the end appear to be no other than he is, a prince of darkneſſe, a black griſely Divel, Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy, and cenſorious Slander, the diſcovery of which, is the worke I am at preſent engaged in, the deſigne of this following Vindication: a worke it is no leſſe difficult and dangerous, then trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and unpleaſing, in reſpect of my ſelfe who write, the things vvhereof I write, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt whom I write.</p>
            <p>Weakneſſe is entailed upon my Sex in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and for my ſelfe in particular, <hi>I</hi> am a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed worme, a woman full of naturall and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:170370:3"/>
infirmities; the chiefeſt of Sinners, and leaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Saints: ſhould the Lord contend with me, I muſt lay my hand upon my mouth, I muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to be juſt and righteous in ſuffering them to deale thus with me; neither ſhould I put my ſelfe to the trouble of a Vindication, but leave the clearing of my Innocency to that day which he hath appointed to judge the world in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I have cauſe to remember, and be aſhamed before the Lord, there being Iniquity even in my holy things; yet as to them, my heart doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach mee, but on the contrary, I have great cauſe of rejoycing, in the uprightneſse of my heart, as to the things of God, and in my abundant love and affections unto them, my heart was enlarged in love towards them, and therefore my mouth was opened upon all occaſions for their good: though I was of a ſtamering Tongue, ſlow of ſpeech, and wanted eloquence, yet the deſire I had of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, made me forward to ſpeake to them in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and in particular: the Lord knowes I lie not, my conſcience alſo bearing me witneſse. I mourned with them that mourned, rejoyced with them that rejoyced; when any were under tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or afflictions, I did labour to ſympathiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with them, as if they were mine owne, and did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage for them at the Throne of Grace as for my ſelfe. And as for that which I did oppoſe among them, it was matter of mourning unto mee, when I apprehended the glory of Chriſt, and their parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb facs="tcp:170370:3"/>
intereſt, could not ſtand together, I then withſtood them, reſolving not to ſpare any that ſtood in the way of Chriſt, and the Goſpels enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is my comfort that the Lord ſeeth not as man ſeeth, man looketh on the outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but the Lord looketh on the heart: not he that commendeth himſelfe, but he whom the Lord commendeth is approved. Though they have proceeded to Cenſure me, and have been full of Curſing and bitterneſſe, returning evill for good; yet I ſhall pray, Lord lay not this ſin to their charge: they know not what Spirit they are of.</p>
            <p>Beſides my perſonall weakneſſes, the many Family-cares that lie upon me, muſt needs unfit me for ſuch a worke, and very much diſinable me to write even of thoſe things which were newly done, and freſh in my memory, much more to write of theſe, which they charged me with, being ſome of them tranſacted Seaven or Eight yeares ſince: In the laying down of which, if my memory ſhould fail me, I need not tell thee (if thou knoweſt <hi>Mr. Stucley</hi> and his Congregation) what an improvement they will make thereof, for the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying of their late unchriſtian Cenſure, of whom I have cauſe to complaine, as the Church in the words of Jeremiah, <hi>Lam. 3.53. they have cut off my life in the dungeon, and caſt a ſtone upon me, which they threaten to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> Surely they who have been ſo wicked as to cenſure me without any ground, will not ſtick to take hold of the leaſt occaſion for the maintaining
<pb facs="tcp:170370:4"/>
of it, and though I have in part been cleared by the Miniſters of <hi>Exeter</hi> from their forged accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who received me jointly into communion with them, yet my Adverſaries being ſo crafty, cruell, and powerfull, it will be no hard matter for them to beare downe all their gain-ſayers; whoſoever ſhall dare to contradict them, unleſſe the Lord himſelfe take them in hand, and then though they are mightier then I, yet they will find to their coſt, that he is higher then they, to him I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted my way, in him is my truſt, therefore my confidence is, that he will bring it to paſse, ſeeing my undertaking is not ſo much for my ſelfe, as for the Lord, for his ſervants and for his people.</p>
            <p>It cannot be (whatever <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stucley</hi> ſayes to the contrary, <hi>p. 46.</hi> of his anſwer to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Toby Allen.</hi>) but that a ſlur is caſt (by their cenſuring mee) on the Miniſters and people of God, in this City, it muſt needs reflect very much on them, who have received ſuch a daughter of <hi>Belial;</hi> ſuch a lyer, &amp;c. (as he tels the world confidently enough I am) into communion and fellowſhip with them. <hi>I</hi> looke on it as my duty, to keep the houſe of God pure, to the uttermoſt of my power, which in this caſe <hi>I</hi> cannot doe, without clearing my ſelfe from thoſe crimes layd to my charge. Had <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stucley</hi> dealt ingeniouſly with his Readers, in diſcovering the right and true grounds of his Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>(viz:)</hi> my hearing another Miniſter, whiles <hi>I</hi> was with them, and after my leaving them, my refuſing to returne, unleſſe <hi>I</hi> might have
<pb facs="tcp:170370:4"/>
the liberty of communion with other of Gods people in this City, then it would have been apparent, that their cenſuring mee was no other then the ſmiting of the watchmen, for ſeeking after my beloved, and ſo have freed mee from a great deale of trouble: But ſeeing he hath dealt ſo craftily as to omit them, and lay other things to my charge in their place, it will be worth the while a little to uncaſe him in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſons, for the undeceiving of thoſe, who (by his two Books) may be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to thinke that <hi>M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi> Allen</hi> and my ſelfe are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed children of hell, and fitter for fellowſhip with damned ſpirits, then to be aſſociates of the Lords people; <hi>p. 11.</hi> True Acc: And that they on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide are a ſelfe denying people, trampling the world under their feet, keeping judgement and doing righteouſneſſe at all times, having their hands filled with both the Tables, and an equall reſpect to all Gods Commandements, <hi>pag. 13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this end <hi>I</hi> ſhall declare,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ground of my joyning with them; and here <hi>I</hi> cannot but take ſhame to my ſelfe, for being ſo raſh; as becauſe of their ſpecious pretences, to forſake the ſocietie of Gods people, and joine with them, before <hi>I</hi> ſaw what worke they woul make.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the manner of our joining together, and my coming in unto them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſome remarkable paſſages, <hi>I</hi> obſerved whiles <hi>I</hi> was with them, together with my beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour in reproofe, admonition, and admiſſion of members.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:170370:5"/>Fourthly, declare the grounds of the difference between us, and of my leaving them, and alſo how I left them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, wipe off the reproaches they have caſt upon mee, ſince my leaving them.</p>
            <p>All which I ſhall ſet upon in the ſtrength of Chriſt, who is able to make the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and the weake things of the world to confound the mighty: And never had a poore creature greater cauſe to flie for refuge to the hope ſet before mee in the Goſpel, to get within the vaile, and ſhrowd my ſelfe under the wings of the Almighty, till theſe calamities be overpaſt, then I have: my enemies are many, and I am ſingle; they wiſe, or rather crafty, I ſimple; they mighty, I weake; they have witneſſes (as <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stucley</hi> affirmes) I none; and which is worſt of all, by accuſing mee of lying, by making me a notorious lyar, they have endeavoured to ſtop the eares of the people, and take them off from believing, and giving credit to what I write: ſo that if the Lord doth not bring forth my righteouſneſse as the light, and my judgement as the noone day, I can looke for none other then to become a Prey (by my writing) unto thoſe who wait for my halting, who have (as farre as I can perceive) taken up a reſolution, (according to the Elders threatning) to make my going away coſt mee dearer, then my coming among them, its true, <hi>I have not yet reſiſted unto blood,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170370:5"/>
yet <hi>I</hi> know not how ſoon <hi>I</hi> may, they have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to deprive mee of my good name, which is of more worth then riches, and the next in eſteeme to life it ſelfe. And what they will do next, had they power in their hands, the Lord knowes! it is to be feared that they who have beene ſo forward to Smite with the Tongue, will not be backward to ſtrike with the hand, when occaſion ſhall ſerve: The Papiſts, when they had put a Cap upon the head of <hi>John Huſſe,</hi> on which were painted ſeverall ugly devils, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after caſt him into the fire: if that which was his lot, and the lot of other ſervants of God, be mine, the will of the Lord be done: It is my reſolution to part with all, rather then returne to ſuch a backſliding, and ſelfe ſeeking people: And therefore my requeſt is unto you, the Miniſters of Chriſt in this Nation, that you would take my caſe into your ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and call <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Stucley</hi> to an account, for his diſorderly ſmiting his fellow-ſervants: That you, who have ſo openly declared againſt Separation, and charged it as a duty on ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to returne into the fold of Chriſt, would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage others to follow our example, by defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us againſt the aſſaults and endeavours of thoſe who have dealt ſo outragiouſly with us, upon no other account then our leaving them, and returning unto you, as it will appeare in the following Narrative and Vindication, from
<pb facs="tcp:170370:6"/>
which <hi>I</hi> ſhall no longer detaine you, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and ſhut up all with this requeſt, that you would in the examination of what I have ſaid, not looke to words or expreſſions which may not be ſo fitly placed, but to the things themſelves, and the truth of them, which was the chiefe ayme (in writing) of her, who ſtill profeſseth herſelfe to be an engaged ſervant to Jeſus Chriſt in Goſpel bonds</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SUSANNA PARR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170370:6"/>
            <head>NARRATIVE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee were told in the time of the Warres, that when the Lord did turne our Captivity, there muſt be a thorough Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, every thing muſt be brought to the patterne in the Mount; and by ſome, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no Reformation, then a partiall Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and in ſpeciall, the laſt warre by many was ſtiled a Sacramentall warre.</p>
            <p>Conſiderations of this nature made me wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to engage where was moſt purity as to the Ordinances, and the great affection and good opinion I had of the <hi>New-England</hi> Churches, made mee in liking with the Congregationall way: Beſides it is well knowne,<note place="margin">Explicit Cov.</note> how much was ſpoken of a Church State, and the priviledges thereof: A greater effuſion of the Spirit, more purity and holineſſe, more union and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, more liberty of Conſcience, and freedome from that yoke of being ſervants unto men, in this Church State, then could be found elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: Many ſuch conſiderations made me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in this way, which we did after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170370:7"/>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Stucley</hi> being at <hi>Torrington,</hi> and coming often to this City, ſpeaking very much in commendation of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Bartlets</hi> Church at <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and the order therein, and alſo exhorting mee, and others to meet together, telling us that we did not live like Chriſtians, becauſe we had not communion one with another, and that we muſt come together, ſo that we might be in a capacity of having the ordinances; we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon met very often, the time was ſpent in praying, and ſpeaking one to another, what God had done for our ſoules: And to this we were enjoyned ſecrecie, the reaſon was given, becauſe we might be put upon ſuch te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations (if it were knowne) as wee could not reſiſt. This practiſe wee continued once or twice a weeke for a long time, M. <hi>Stucley</hi> promiſing to be at our meetings, which he accordingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed ſometimes. At length ſome of us de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to have the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and becauſe of that confuſion which was among us, in that we wanted abilities for the right managing of our weekly Exerciſes, wee deſired likewiſe to have a Miniſter, M. <hi>Hanmer</hi> was pitcht upon by ſome, but oppoſed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in the end wee agreed to leave it to M. <hi>Barlet</hi> of <hi>Brideford,</hi> whether M. <hi>Hanmer,</hi> or M. <hi>Stucley</hi> was the fitteſt for us, hereupon wee ſent meſſengers to M. <hi>Bartlet,</hi> who when they came to his houſe found M. <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe there, M. <hi>Bartlet</hi> told the meſſengers, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170370:7"/>
M. <hi>Stucley</hi> was fitteſt for the preſent: but however hee would acquaint M. <hi>Hanmer</hi> with the buſineſſe, which he did, but M. <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> refuſed it. After this M. <hi>Stucley</hi> came to continue in this City, yet not quitting <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rington</hi> till the meanes was ſetled on him here. And now againe ſome of us (the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were very indifferent) renewed our former deſires of having the Sacrament, and ſent about it to M. <hi>Bartlet,</hi> who ſaid, we were not as yet in a capacity to have that Ordinance, that it was neceſſary we ſhould be firſt in a Goſpel order embodied: and ſaid moreover, that then wee ſhould ſee much of God, that the day of our embodying would be ſuch a day as we had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeene. A while after M. <hi>Bartlet</hi> came to the City with his Church officers, he himſelfe prayed and preached on <hi>Zech.</hi> 6.12. in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, afterwards ſeven or eight perſons ſpake out the experiences they had of the change of their condition, with which I was much affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and through M. <hi>Stucleys</hi> perſwaſion did the like. Afterwards there was a confeſſion of faith read, being a Copy of that which was compoſed by M. <hi>Hughes,</hi> which Copy we had not from the Author, but from another, this confeſſion of faith was ſubſcribed by every one of us. And then M. <hi>Bartlet</hi> made ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals unto us by way of <hi>quaere,</hi> to this effect as I remember.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170370:8"/>1. Whether we would take Chriſt for our Judge, King, and Law-giver.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether wee would renounce all wayes of falſe worſhip?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether wee would worſhip God in all his Ordinances?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether we would give up our ſelves to the Lord, and one to another, and would engage our ſelves in all duties of Chriſtianity each un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether wee would hold communion with other Churches?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether wee would relieve the Saints that were in Communion, according to our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether we would not reſt in the light that we had received, but would ſtudy to know the mind of God, and live up unto it?</p>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of our engagement, as I remember. At this time and ſomewhile after, there was never a woman of the Church but my ſelfe, and yet at every meeting about Church affaires Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> would ſend for mee, and when I pleaded for my abſence (at ſuch times) from the meetings, that of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Let your women keep ſilence in the Church,</hi> for it is not permitted unto them to ſpeake; he replyed, he would do nothing without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the whole. And when I was preſent, he himſelfe would conſtraine me to ſpeak my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of things propoſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170370:8"/>We were (as I ſaid formerly) very deſirous of the Sacrament, in order to which, our firſt work was to get a Miniſter that might adminiſter it.</p>
            <p>Although Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> was with us, yet the people of <hi>Torrington</hi> claimed an engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from him, that Towne having been viſited with the plague, and deprived of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters maintenance. Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> (who was their Miniſter) for thoſe reaſons left them; but with a promiſe of returning ſo ſoon as the Lord ſhould remove his hand, and ſufficient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for a Miniſter ſhould be procured, both which being at this time effected, we could not chuſe him to be an Officer, untill he were by them freed from his engagement: in order here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto much meanes was uſed, Maſter <hi>Bartlet</hi> was imployed to perſwade them unto it; but they with one conſent refuſed it, ſaying, that ſeeing he had promiſed to returne, they expected that he ſhould keep promiſe with them.</p>
            <p>Hereupon we wrote for counſell to ſome of the Congregationall Churches in London, Maſter <hi>Feake,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Harriſon</hi> (in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to our Letters) affirmed that Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> was bound in conſcience to goe unto <hi>Torrington:</hi> that it would be diſhonourable to the Goſpel to leave them, unleſſe he could get their conſent for his diſmiſſion. At length Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe accompanied with two or three of the Church rode thither, where having
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170370:9"/>
made an agreement with the people, thoſe that rode with him were called in to conſent therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which they accordingly did.</p>
            <p>At their returne Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> required each one of us to conſent likewiſe unto the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they made at <hi>Torrington,</hi> without decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what it was; which being done by all the men, he deſired the ſiſters (there being other women now added to the Church) to do the like, which my ſelfe and ſome others refuſed, reſolving that we would not act by an implicite faith. Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> thereupon ſaid, that what was done was a Church act, becauſe they who went with him conſented thereunto <hi>(viz.)</hi> that we were engaged to get a Miniſter for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Torrington.</hi> Accordingly there was one procured, who continued with them for a time.</p>
            <p>This Serpentine ſubtilty of his I tooke ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall notice of, and did for it reprove him to his face: we were in the meane time (and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for ſome yeares) in a bewildred conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without either of the Sacraments, ſome not having their children baptized in a long time, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did procure ſome Congregationall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to do it. And as for the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, they who would partake of it; rode to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places in the Country: moſt of the people were very indifferent whether we had the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances or no, ſeeking themſelves, getting pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and offices, deſigning how they might build
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170370:9"/>
their owne houſes: and as for Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe, he was ſo diſtracted with Law-ſuits, Intangled with the world and mony engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as that he was ſeldome with us at our faſts and times of prayer.</p>
            <p>Hence I began to ſuſpect, that they intended nothing but ſeparation, and ſetting up of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their owne intereſts and deſignes, which did exceedingly trouble mee.</p>
            <p>Upon our private faſt dayes, when wee had done praying, it was our cuſtome (for the help of thoſe that were to pray) to ſpend a little time in Conference, and at ſuch times did I take occaſion to ſpeak of the diſorders among us, &amp; told the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plainly, that I feard we did ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others more godly then our ſelves, as <hi>Cain,</hi> who went out from the preſence of the Lord to build citties; that there was little regard had to what we at firſt pretended, the ſetting up of pure ordinances; I often told them that I never heard or read in Scripture, or other hiſtory, that the Lord did make uſe of a people of ſuch an earthly, luke-warme, and indifferent ſpirit, in any publique worke of reformation; that it was not a party, or confederacy that I looked after, but to have the Goſpel more diſcovered in greater light and beauty; and the ordinances to be enjoyed in greater purity: the beauty of Gods ornament to be ſet in Majeſtie, and more purity and ſelfe-deniall to appeare in us, who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170370:10"/>
had ſeparated from all mixtures.</p>
            <p>Becauſe I conceive that purity lay onely in this way, therefore was I very forward and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in it, hoping to leave poſterity the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances pure, and the name of God glorious in the brightneſſe of the Goſpel: for this cauſe did I deale ſo plainly with them; with which plaine and faithfull dealing, they pretended many times to be much affected, and thereupon would do ſomething more in order to Religion, then they had formerly.</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> (as I ſaid before) being trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about the things of this world, left us to our ſelves very often in our meetings: ſo that it is not to be wondred at, if in them there were much ſtrange fire, both in prayer and expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Scriptures, they being meere Novices, and in the entrance of Chriſtianity, and many of them ſcarce well principled, I feared that the name of God was often taken in vain in prayer, ſure I am that much ignorance, pride, and ſelfe confidence, and a <hi>Diotrephes</hi> ſpirit ſtrongly working, appeared in many of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">N.E.</note>One of them affirmed, that there was no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the holy things &amp;c. this being deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without any caution when the meeting was publique, I told him of it in private the ſame day.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Owen.</note>Another who had formerly beene an Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt, then a Seeker, next (as I was informed)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170370:10"/>
a Papiſt, or little better, very much addicted to the ſtudy of their bookes, the moſt conviction that he had (as was reported) was by <hi>Jonas Ware,</hi> ſince a Roman Catholique, who went to Rome, and then turning to prelacy, and the booke of Common-prayer, and afterward an Independent, the ſame perſon was very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at our meetings, and did often put forth himſelfe in the duty of prayer, which was a great trouble to mee to heare how the name of God was taken in vaine by him, inſomuch as that I earneſtly deſired Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> to hinder him from engaging in that duty, till he underſtood the nature of it better.</p>
            <p>I acquainted him likewiſe of other diſorders and miſcarriages very frequent at our meetings, declaring how much I was troubled at them; for redreſſe of which, I intreated him to be conſtantly with us. But he endeavoured to quiet me with this, that they were honeſt, though weak, and further perſwaded me to be conſtant at the meetings, to be faithfull unto them, in minding them of what was amiſſe. I told him it was more fit for me to be in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate meditation, to be gathering rather then ſcattering: but he replyed, that the time was now not to be Cloſet-Profeſſors, but to ſay, <hi>come, let us go up to the houſe of the Lord, to ſeek the Lord together, with our faces Zion-ward.</hi> And though I pleaded my Sex, my naturall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170370:11"/>
and ſinfull infirmities, which made me unfit to ſpeak unto others, yet he preſſed it on me as my duty. And when there was any Jarring between them and my ſelfe, he deſired me not to be troubled, though I met with oppoſition, that one was of a Souldierly ſpirit, another of a dull Spirit, that it was meere Envy, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to ſpeak with them about it himſelfe. Yea when I reſolved to be ſilent at ſome mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe would ſingle me out, and even conſtraine me to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>As concerning my Carriage at the Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of members, I ſhall give a briefe account of it as followeth.</p>
            <p>They who deſired admiſſion into the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, were ſometimes deſired in a private mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſpeak what experience they had of the worke of grace upon their Soules: after which we were every one of us both men and women to declare our thoughts of what was ſpoken; it being laid down as a ground, that we muſt have an account of a change from a naturall and legall eſtate, into an eſtate of grace and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, of thoſe whom we admitted into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us. I among the reſt did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my weak meaſure declare my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which I thought would not ſtand for grace. I was ſo far from delighting in this work, as that it was a trouble to me, an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment from which I would willingly have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170370:11"/>
been freed: I conceived it more needfull for my ſelfe to ſtudy the worrd, and compare my own heart with the rule, then to be ſo taken up about the condition of others. But this was our principle, we were to keep the houſe of God pure, we were ſet as Porters at the door, it was our duty, we were not to be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at ſuch times, yea it was our liberty, that we, who were to have communion with thoſe vvho came to be admitted, ſhould give in our aſſent, or diſſent in reference to their admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I did therefore at ſuch times declare my thoughts aſvvell as the reſt, but left the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to themſelves, as it appeares in <hi>Gani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> vvho vvas admitted, though I vvas at the firſt againſt his admiſſion. I mention him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he vvas brought by Mr. <hi>Eveleigh,</hi> as an Inſtance of my cenſoriouſneſſe. I vvas blamed for diſliking him, vvhom they ſaid vvas one of the moſt eminent among them, and yet it vvas not long after, before he diſcovered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by Renouncing the principles of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and turning <hi>Quaker.</hi> He in ſpeaking out his Experiences pretended unto much Joy and raviſhment of Spirit, but (the Lord knovves) vvhen he ſpake of ſuch enjoyments, he ſpake as a ſtranger that never intermedled vvith this Joy, never declaring any povverfull effect thereof, but only that vvhich vvas, only but a <hi>Balaams</hi> vviſh. I the rather inſtance in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170370:12"/>
him, becauſe he was the firſt that kindled the fire of Contention, which then brake out in that manner, as it is not quenched to this day; here began the Quarrell on their part. When I was called by the Elder to give in my thoughts concerning a Perſon propoſed, he moſt diſorderly intercepted me, for which there vvas not the leaſt admonition given him: but not long after his folly was made manifeſt, by his Caſting off the very forme of godlineſſe. This is one and the Cheife one of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom I diſliked, though approved of by the Church. If I be contentious for oppoſing ſuch a one, let me be contentious ſtill; though none among them will witneſſe for me, yet he doth, he ſtands to this day as a ſad witneſſe between me and them, whether I were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in my oppoſitions, or they infallible in their determinations. Beſides, as for ſome who continue among them, if you look for diſtinguiſhing Characters, they are ſcarcely viſible, much leſſe eaſy to be diſcerned.</p>
            <p>Thus I did from time to time, whilſt we were without Officers and Ordinances, partly through the great deſire I had to promote the worke of Reformation among us, partly through Mr <hi>Stucley's</hi> inſtigation reprove them for their indifferency of Spirit, ſtir them up to that which I conceived vvas their duty, for vvhich I alvvaies gave them my grounds and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170370:12"/>
reaſons. But after the officers vvere choſen, I never medled (to my remembrance) vvith Church affaires, nor ſpake in the meetings, after I heard by Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> my ſpeaking vvas diſreliſht; unleſſe a Queſtion vvas propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and I vvas deſired to give my Anſvver unto it.</p>
            <p>Not long after, the Officers vvere choſen, I being at Mr. <hi>Stucley's</hi> houſe, deſired him to reſolve me concerning a true Church, he then confeſſed that the Churches of <hi>New England</hi> did acknovvledge the Churches of <hi>old England,</hi> from vvhence we had ſeparated, to be true Churches: I told him thereupon that vve could not juſtifie our Separation. At length vve falling into diſcourſe of other things, he ſaid my ſpeaking vvas diſreliſht by ſome; I anſvvered, that I did not like it my ſelfe, and therefore vvould be from thenceforth ſilent, though I looked on it as my duty formerly, he told me no, he vvould have me ſpeak, but it muſt be by a Brother; for a ſtander by may ſee more then he that plaies the game, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing likewiſe if I did ſpeak by him, to deliver my words in the ſame manner as I ſpake them.</p>
            <p>After this it pleaſed the Lord to exerciſe me with a ſmarting affliction, the death of a dear child; the ſuddenneſſe of the ſtroke, and ſome other circumſtances made it a very mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting affliction. When my Bovvels vvere yer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170370:13"/>
towards my child, I called to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the Lords tender bowels towards his children, for whom he had given his only Son; when I conſidered the breach that the Lord had made in my family, I beheld how terrible it was to make a breach in his family. Then the worke I was ingaged in, this Sin of Separation, appeared nakedly unto me to be no other then a vvounding of Chriſts body, vvhich is his Church, the Church vvhich he hath purchaſed vvith his ovvn blood: I then looked on Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to be a dividing of Chriſt. Truly I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held it vvith terror, this ſin of vvounding of Chriſt it made a vvound in my ſoule, vvhich vvas kept open in a terrible manner, the Lord bringing to my remembrance his Juſtice and ſeverity, and vvrath revealed from heaven on families and nations, yea on his ovvn people, ever ſince the beginning of the vvorld: as alſo his Judgments vvhich are in the earth to this day, from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the <hi>Revelation</hi> vvas brought to my remembrance, and kept hard upon me. Having theſe Impreſſions on my Spirit, I vvas almoſt overwhelmed, and in mine ovvn apprehenſion upon the Borders of Hell, vvhere the Lord made me to behold the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his vvrath upon ſinners: I could then have told vvhat hel vvas, I felt the flaſhings of helfire in my ſoule, the vvrath of God that lay hard upon me, the effects vvhereof vvere very
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170370:13"/>
terrible, inſomuch as I was even ſwallowed up, only the Lord was pleaſed to keep me follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after him, reſolving to lie at his feet, though he ſhould ſpurne me to hell. Having thus been under a ſentence of death with the very terrors of hell in my ſoule, providence ſo ordering it, I came (by following the people) where Mr. FORD preached. I no ſooner came into the Congregation, but I was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly troubled, as that I vented my ſelfe in Paſſionate teares; fearing leſt I might be unfit to hear, but in prayer recovered my ſelfe. His text was in <hi>John</hi> 16: laſt. <hi>Be of good cheere, I have overcome the world.</hi> He inſtanced in all the enemies of the new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the World, the God of this world, Sin, Death, and Hell: the Lord ſetting it home every ſentence was to me as the rivetting of the nailes, ſet on by the great maſter of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and in prayer afterward (the Lord ſo providing) thoſe very particulars which were the burden of my ſoule, were put up unto God. I went out of the congregation with another frame of ſpirit then when I came in, bleſſing the Lord for giving his Son Jeſus Chriſt, who hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood, and hath made us Kings and Prieſts unto God. But afterwards I began to queſtion whether I had not taken that, which did not belong unto me, Chriſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170370:14"/>
then ſpeaking comfort to his diſciples in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to that hardſhip they were to meet with in the world; among the reſt of their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings this was one, that they ſhould be put out of the Synagogues, yea the time would come that whoſoever killed them, would think he did God good ſervice, which things Chriſt told them that they might not be offended: But yet the Sermon being in generall of all the Enemies of the new Creature, I could not put it off. Furthermore the appearance of God was ſo remarkable in the change of my ſpirit, as that I could not but take it home, that Sins of the right hand and left hand, and ſeparation alſo, and death and hell ſhould be caſt into the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone, that in the meane time Chriſt hath overcome the world, the Prince of this world is judged, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned already, only the execution is defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red till the time appointed by the father. And as for ſufferings, that we muſt look for them, having ſuch proviſion ſo remarkably laid in before, I cannot but take notice of it at preſent. But then I could not conceive how it was likely for me to ſuffer in that kind, there being then ſo much love pretended. But now the time is come, and therefore I mention it: Chriſt ſaieth, theſe things have I ſpoken unto you, that when the time ſhall come, you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that I told you of them. Now I can
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170370:14"/>
make application of all the Sermon which is food for my faith to live upon, although I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer as an evill doer. I mention it with admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Lord even then when he ſpake peace unto me after my being convinced of Separation, ſhould lay alſo proviſion againſt Excommunication.</p>
            <p>But now after my conviction of Separation, it troubled me very much, becauſe I knew not how to avoid it: my fear was leſt I ſhould be conſtrained to live in it, had I preſently come off, I ſhould have made a breach there. They pretended ſo much love unto me, as I knew not which way to break this bond, which the Apoſtle calls the bond of perfectneſſe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reſolved to wait upon the Lord, for the opening a way unto me, which he did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in manner following.</p>
            <p>The Lord was making ſuch abundant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for me in Mr. <hi>Ford's</hi> miniſtry, I did conſtantly attend thereon, hearing him once a Lords day for the moſt part, unleſſe it were when we had the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per adminiſtred among us. This was my practice ever ſince he came to this City, of which Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> took no great notice before he was in office; but afterward both he and the people were diſpleaſed with me for it, on which began the quarrell on my part between us. Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> being a ſtranger was employed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170370:15"/>
to take me off from this practice, who at firſt pretended that it did very much trouble him, but ſince he hath told me that he wiſhed that he had never been put upon it.</p>
            <p>He ſent a Meſſenger unto me to perſwade me to leave Mr. <hi>Ford's</hi> miniſtry: I then ſhewed my grounds for that practice, what proviſion I found there, and how the Lord had made that miniſtry effectuall unto me, and withall that when I came among them, I took up a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to attend upon that miniſtry.</p>
            <p>The ſame day in a publique meeting they accuſed me firſt of Contention, and ſecondly for my hearing Mr. <hi>Ford,</hi> which (as the Elder ſaid) the Church neither could nor would bear, however they would not medle with it for that time.</p>
            <p>As to the Article of Contention <hi>I</hi> appealed to the Church, and charged them to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as they would anſwer it another day, in making it known whether they had found me Contentious.</p>
            <p>Upon which, <hi>I</hi> having withdrawn my ſelfe, they entred into a debate about it, every one declaring their thoughts of me: the reſult of which debate was this.</p>
            <p>That they neither could nor would charge me with contention for a world, but did fear that through a mixture of Corruption it might tend to contention. This buſineſſe was ended
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170370:15"/>
three daies after, they declaring that they were ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>But as to the other Article the Elder told me the very next day, when <hi>I</hi> preſſed him to declare whether he knew of any thing againſt mee, he told mee that there was nothing elſe in the world but my hearing Maſter <hi>Forde,</hi> and then deſired me to leave off that practiſe; which I did ſometimes to content them, but the little peace that I found in it, made me quickly to take it up againe.</p>
            <p>After this meſſengers were ſent unto me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times from the Church, to informe me how my practice was diſliked by ſome, to whom I gave my reaſons for it as formerly, and told them farther, that I was engaged to ſtudy the mind of Chriſt; and becauſe of their diſ-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, to ſeeke the Lord in this thing, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed likewiſe to ſubmit my ſelfe to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, ſo as to be accountable to them of my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Forde.</hi> I informed them alſo, how the Lord had made uſe of that Miniſtry for my good in theſe times of diſtraction, I gave the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thanks for the great love, &amp; good will they ſeemed to bear towards me, but withall deſired the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to be offended if I made uſe of my Chriſtian liberty till I was better informed, and told them <hi>where the Carkaſſe is, there will the Eagles reſort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> alſo ſent me two long letters, wherein he endeavored to perſwade me to have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170370:16"/>
dependance only on their miniſtry without hearing any other.</p>
            <p>But when they ſaw that I could not be taken off from this practice, they began to quarrell with me, telling me that I was contentious, that it was heighth of ſpirit, and ſo by little and little eſtranged themſelves. But the Word was a light unto me, and ſo evident, as if it had been appointed on purpoſe for direction, they themſelves being judges, inſomuch as ſome of them asked me whether I did not uſe to viſit Mr. <hi>Ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> he declared in his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique miniſtry oftentimes, That it was out of the way of order to hear any other miniſter, when our own officers preached, that no bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing was to be expected in ſuch a way, and if ſo be there were any profit received, it was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, a temptation, yea a judgment of God upon ſuch a ſoule; it was a going out of the boſome of Chriſt into the boſome of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; Rebellion againſt Chriſt, and that ſuch muſt be dealt with as Traytors and Rebells.</p>
            <p>At length a faſt, a day of humiliation was appointed for the diſorderly walking of ſome, and that with obſtinacy in the generall.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I went unto Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> to know for what end this faſt was intended, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was in reference to my ſelf; if ſo, <hi>I</hi> ſhould remove the occaſion, reſolving with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170370:16"/>
my ſelfe, if the liberty of hearing other mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were denied me, to leave them. But he and Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> found with him, in ſtead of informing me fell into a diſpute about true Churches, a ſubject that <hi>I</hi> was unskilfull in, and he by reaſon of his deafneſſe unfit to treat of, and withall let fall ſome ſtrange Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions concerning the people of God. <hi>I</hi> told him that <hi>I</hi> did delight in the image of God where ever <hi>I</hi> found it, in thoſe that were the Excellent of the Earth, that did excell in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: he then endeavoured to perſwade me that I was to have my affections tyed up to thoſe of their Society, alleadging that <hi>I</hi> might aſwell delight in another man that was not my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, becauſe the Image of God ſhined more in him then in my husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. I being troubled at this groſſe diſcourſe told him that thoſe relations were of a different nature, and that I thought I did owe more duty where God in his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence had caſt me, and where I had the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity and ability to performe it, then I was engaged unto or could diſcharge unto others, where <hi>I</hi> had no ſuch opportunities: yet <hi>I</hi> did not look upon it as that which could cut off my affections from the people of God, from thoſe who had the Image of God renewed in them. Something alſo was ſpoken of Church ordinances, Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> ſaid the preaching of the vvord vvas not a Church ordinance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170370:17"/>
that it might be preached by one that was not a Church officer, and it might be uſed out of a Church, even in a family. For my own part <hi>I</hi> knew not how to underſtand theſe diſtinctions, but accounted them ſtrange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> ſome dayes after in a letter taxed me for acknowledging an aſſembly of people to be a Church meeting, and the wedneſday meeting to be a Church meeting which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>I</hi> lookt upon as <hi>Babylon.</hi> To which <hi>I</hi> returned Anſwer by letter, that <hi>I</hi> accounted thoſe from whom we did ſeparate a true Church, as he had told me the New England miniſters did; that <hi>I</hi> lookt upon the wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies meeting to be a Church meeting, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters as ambaſſadors of Chriſt, the preaching of the word a Church ordinance, that which Chriſt hath appointed for the gathering in, building up, and edifying of his body, which is the Church, that <hi>I</hi> did put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween hearing there and among our ſelves in point of efficacy, and that my ſeparation from them was not in doctrine and worſhip, but in diſcipline. Much <hi>I</hi> wrote likewiſe for the removing of ſome prejudices, complaining how I was preached againſt, and prayed againſt; informing him likewiſe that <hi>I</hi> was neither able to live in the fire of contention, nor ſit down under a miniſtry that I could not profit by, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170370:17"/>
therfore ſhould willingly withdrawe from them, I alſo deſired him that whileſt wee contended for pure ordinances we ſhould not ſuffer the Goſpell to be corrupted, and that I feared we did not walke up to our owne principles, and I likewiſe deſired direction from him.</p>
            <p>When the day appointed for the faſt was come, I went to the meeting not knowing for what it was intended, The practice of the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of other miniſters was then made to be as the Sin of <hi>Korah</hi> and <hi>Dathan</hi> And betweene the ſeverall prayers Mr <hi>Stoneha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> propounded ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what by way of queſtion, how to know an heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke: one diſcovery was when perſons went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their owne principles as thoſe did, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they have given up themſelves on unto another ſhall notwithſtanding ſay they delight in the Image of God where ever they finde it, in the Excellent ones of the earth, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their principles and deſtructive to the very fundementalls of the Church.</p>
            <p>This being contrary in my apprehenſion to that of the Apoſtle. 2 <hi>Col,</hi> where he tels us. That he had greate conflict. not for them only which he knew, But alſo for as many (of the Saints) as had not ſeene his face in the fleſh, And in <hi>Chap:</hi> 1.4. where he commends them for their love to all the Saints, <hi>I</hi> did in the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tell ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> privately, There was that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd which could not be prov'd by the word.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170370:18"/>The Sacrament of the Lords Supper had beene about this time omitted for neer halfe a yeare, ſure I am it was very long, I enquired of ſome the reaſon thereof, who told me becauſe <hi>I</hi> could not ſit downe with Maſter <hi>Stoneham's</hi> miniſtry, whereupon I went to Maſter <hi>Stoneham</hi> to know the reaſon why the Sacrament was kept from us, at the firſt he gave me no anſwer, but when I was earneſt with him to give me ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, he ſaid, that he did not know what uſe I would make of it: I then told him, hee looked upon me as under a temptation, when I was in an ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt; but I had cauſe to feare that he was under a temptation, in negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ſuch an ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, which he had a command often to make uſe of; and then intreated him that if he thought me unworthy to partake of it, that I onely might be kept off, that the ordinance might not (upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count) be laid aſide: to this he replied, that the prayers they had put up, would be anſwered, which was all the ſatisfaction I could get from him at that time: A weeke after I preſſed him againe for the Sacrament, he then told me, that if I would not ſit downe under his miniſtry he would be no officer unto mee, and for a cloſe told mee, there was one who had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what againſt mee: whereupon the ſame day I went to Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> to know what it was that ſome body had againſt mee, what the evill
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170370:18"/>
was they could charge me with, I told him that it was my deſire and endeavour <hi>to keep a good conſcience void of offence both towards God and towards men:</hi> that if there were any evill with which they could charge mee, upon information what it was, I would not continue in the practice thereof, and therefore deſired him to tell mee what it was, that one had againſt mee: to which Maſter <hi>Stoneham,</hi> then being at Maſter <hi>Stucleys</hi> houſe, anſwered, that I muſt firſt reſolve to ſit down under their miniſtry, and then they would conferre about that: <hi>I</hi> replyed that <hi>I</hi> did not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, but in diſtinguiſhing ordinances, unto which this anſwer was returned, that there was as much reaſon for a woman to goe after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man becauſe of fruitfulneſſe, as to make uſe of another Miniſtry becauſe of more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. At which groſſe diſcovery of themſelves <hi>I</hi> reſolved with my ſelfe to take my leave of them: Maſter <hi>Stucley</hi> at my going forth came with mee to the doore, and then deſired me to deny my ſelfe-holineſſe for God, and look for a reward in heaven: This was the laſt time that ever <hi>I</hi> was in his houſe.</p>
            <p>After this two or three times <hi>I</hi> went to Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> the Elder, to know what it was they had againſt me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but <hi>I</hi> could never ſpeak with him, untill <hi>I</hi> met him at the meeting, where <hi>I</hi> deſired to ſpeak with him, and went to his houſe, and deſired him to informe me, what
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170370:19"/>
they had to Charge mee with, who inſteed of anſwering directly to my queſtion ſayd, there would bee a Sacrament the next Lords day, which (as I remember) was putt of, and that ſome body did deſire mee to forbeare, my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer was, that I ſhould not giue offence to any, he then told mee what a doe they had to pleaſe mee, inſtancing in his wife, dead and buried long before.</p>
            <p>This being all I could learne of him, I went about to ſeuerall perſons (att their houſes) to know what it was that they had againſt mee, but they told mee there was nothinge but my goeing to heare others, then I asked whether the Church had any thinge againſt mee, they did aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure mee the Church had nothing againſt mee, Having done this, I beheld the doore ſtanding ſo wide open, as that I might fairely take my leave, which yet I did not, before <hi>I</hi> had for a while ſeriouſly and ſadly conſidered of theſe following particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſtrangeneſſe of their opinions and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes in reference to the ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt: Preaching was affirmed to be no Church Ordinance, as alſo Catechizing.</p>
            <p>The ordinance of Faſting exceedingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, in which they walked in the wayes of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and ſtatutes of <hi>Omry,</hi> Making it like <hi>Iſmaels</hi> weeping to fall on poore ſoules, when they go to worſhip the Lord, like the tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170370:19"/>
concourſe of people, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.32. by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the perticular occaſions and ends of their faſtings, <hi>faſting</hi> rather <hi>for ſtrife and debate,</hi> then to <hi>keepe the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace</hi> with Gods people.</p>
            <p>The Sacrament of the Lords Supper was for a long time detained, not only from my ſelfe in particular without giving any reaſon, but from the whole Congregation in generall; new, and unheard of, and unſcripturall qualifications were required of thoſe who would pertake thereof: They muſt ſubſcribe and engage not to heare any, but their owne Officers at ſuch times as the Officers did preach, and muſt believe that a greater bleſſing was to be expected on their Miniſtry, then on the Miniſtry of others, when (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>He that planteth, and he that watereth are all one,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7, 8. To come out from among them upon this account I was very much encouraged by Maſter <hi>Burroughs,</hi> who in his heart diviſions, <hi>p.</hi> 174. ſayeth, <hi>If Gouernors enjoyne any thing vppon the Church, or any member thereof that is Sin, or if they ſhall mingle Euill in the Publique worſhip, ſo that there can be noe Ioyning with their worſhip, but there muſt be Ioyning likewiſe with their Sin: In this caſe they are the Schiſmaticks, not thoſe who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea farther If they impoſe that, which is not neceſſary though in it ſelfe not ſinful, and will not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170370:20"/>
beare with the weaknes of ſuch as thinke it Evill: If upon that, they are forced to withdrawe, in this the governors are the Schiſmaticks; the cauſe of the Rent is in them, they ought in ſuch things to beare with the weakneſſes of their brethren, and not imperiouſly require of them thoſe things of which there is no neceſsity, if ſuch things be Sinne to their Brethrens conſciences, if they will ſtand upon it to enjoyne them, they lay a neceſsity on them to withdraw. God will not lay the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Schiſme thus; ſuch a one departed from the Communion of ſuch a church, becauſe he would not doe what was lawfull to be done, But thus, —you impoſed that upon your brother, which there was no neceſsity of, and would not forbeare him in what I would have you to forbeare him, but cauſed him by your imperiouſneſſe, and ſtifneſſe to depart from communion with you. It's true, God ſaith, the things might have been done, but it was not neceſſary, it was out of conſcience to me that they forbore, the weakneſſe is theirs; but the Schiſme is yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From the ordinances I turned my thoughts unto the Churches, both that from which I had ſeparated, as alſo that whereof I was then a member, as to the Churches of England, <hi>I</hi> conſidered that they were right in reſpect of Doctrine and worſhip; and not onely ſo, but that they were united likewiſe by an <hi>implicit covenant,</hi> which upon enquiry that they of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170370:20"/>
New-England make to be the ſame for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with that which is <hi>explicit,</hi> contrarie to what I believed at the firſt (viz.) That an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Covenant</hi> was neceſſary to the <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of a <hi>viſible Church,</hi> and therefore upon this account, there was no reaſon to ſeparate from them: I conſidered that the work of this generation was not the <hi>Conſtituting,</hi> but the <hi>reforming</hi> of Churches, which I conceived ſeparation did hinder. It made my heart bleed within me to think that I ſhould have a hand in the hindering of <hi>Reformation,</hi> for which ſo much precious blood had been ſpilt in the late Warre.</p>
            <p>As to the Church whereof I was then a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I feared what it would come to in the end, there being in ſo ſhort a time, ſuch a viſible difference between our firſt Ingagements, and the preſent ſtate thereof. At the firſt, <hi>liberty of conſcience and freedome</hi> from the Intolerable yoke of being Servants unto men was preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; But now we were in greater bondage then ever, all liberty of diſſenting from them being denyed. Our officers were ſwayed by ſuch a <hi>Prelaticall Spirit,</hi> as that every one muſt reſt ſatisfied with their determinations, otherwiſe it would be lookt upon as a <hi>non-conformity,</hi> contention, and the Lords Supper forthwith denyed them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170370:21"/>At the firſt we were not to reſt in the light we had allready received, but engaged to ſtudy the minde and will of God, and live up unto it, to have Chriſt for our <hi>Judge,</hi> our <hi>Lawgiver</hi> and <hi>King;</hi> but now the voice of the Church (two or three of them) carries all before it, he that did not hearken unto this, he that was not obedient unto this, muſt be preſently accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted contentious, cenſorious, a Rebell againſt Jeſus Chriſt, and dealt withall as ſuch. When I demanded, whether that which they ſaid to be the <hi>voice</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> were the <hi>voice</hi> of <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer was returned, that the <hi>voice</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> was the <hi>voice</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this be true, then we muſt believe as the Church believes, we muſt believe that the Church cannot erre, contrary to that in <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. where we read that the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi> ſaid one thing, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> another, where every one is commanded to <hi>heare what the ſpirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the people; the generalitie of them I plainly perceived that they made it their buſineſſe to ſtudy conformity, without the leaſt heeding what they had formerly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, or enquiring what, for the time to come this might grow unto; <hi>Iſacher-like they bowed their ſhoulders to beare, and became Servants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whatſoever tribute was impoſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170370:21"/>In the laſt place I took a briefe view of their behaviour abroad in the world—where they were ſtriving who ſhould be foremoſt in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of offices and places of profit; ſo imployed they were in enriching themſelves, and building their <hi>own houſes;</hi> as that they little minded the <hi>houſe of God.</hi> And as for Mr <hi>Stucley,</hi> he was ſo entangled with the world as that it took up a great part of his time every week, which ſhould have been ſpent in the worke of the miniſtry, contrary to that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. So troubled he was about many things, as that he very much neglected that one thing needfull, the feeding of the flock,— He ſeemed to me to be led captive by <hi>ambition</hi> and <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> which made him more crafty and politick then could (in my Judgment) ſtand with the <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the Goſpell:</hi> So that I queſtioned whether or no, he had not applied himſelfe to the ſtudie of wiſedome, onely for her left hand bleſſings of riches and honor.</p>
            <p>I cald to mind his ſubtilty in the manageing of many buſieneſſes, his ſetting Mr <hi>Stonham</hi> a worke about that which he durſt not appeare in himſelfe; but eſpecially his <hi>trecherouſneſſe</hi> and deceitfull dealing in uſeing means for the opening reading and Coppying of poſtletters; the letters of the chiefe mageſtrate of this Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, this I was enformed of by one of their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and ſince hath been confirmed by others;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170370:22"/>
And his appointing a day of <hi>thankſgiving</hi> for the Succesfulneſſe of his deſignes furthered by ſuch unlawfull meanes; whether this were not a bringing of <hi>Thankſgiving</hi> with leaven, I leave it to others to Judge. I could not but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from that <hi>thankſgiving:</hi> I conſidered with my ſelfe, how unlike it was that he ſhould be a faithfull miniſter of Chriſt, who dealt ſo unfaithfully with men, and therefore that it could not be ſafe for me to continue any longer under his paſtorall charge; eſpecially ſeeing I could not be faithfull to them, becauſe of their crafty ſeeking advantages to enſnare: All the remedy I had left was to withdrawe from them.</p>
            <p>Thus being convinced of <hi>Separation</hi> and the evill thereof, and having pondred a while of their <hi>Unchriſtian</hi> or rather <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> practiſes, I went on the 24 of <hi>March</hi> 1654. to Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> the Elder, whom <hi>I</hi> deſired to acquaint the Church, that I ſhould continue no longer with them, for ſeverall reaſons which I then gave him; And that <hi>I</hi> would willingly (if they deſired it) give them farther Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction; he replyed that there was nothing but would be made up: <hi>I</hi> know that very well, ſaid <hi>I,</hi> but for ſeverall reaſons <hi>I</hi> am reſolved to withdraw from your ſociety.</p>
            <p>About foureteen daies after, (being ſent for) <hi>I</hi> went to their meeting according to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170370:22"/>
ſuppoſing they would require an account of my leaving of them; but Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether waved that, and inſteed thereof having queſtioned me a little concerning Mr <hi>Stoneham,</hi> demanded how long I had uſed to heare M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Ford;</hi> I anſwered a year at the leaſt, the truth of which aſſertion when he ſeemed to queſtion, I added farther that my writing books would make it appeare that <hi>I</hi> had heard him much longer.</p>
            <p>Then he asked me concerning Mris <hi>Eveleigh,</hi> whether I did not ſpeak againſt her?</p>
            <p>To this I returned Anſwer; (1) by asking him whether he did not ſay to Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> in his own houſe within a few daies after that ſhe was admitted, that I was ſo farre from ſpeaking againſt her, as that I had ſpoken for her, and therefore would cleare me.</p>
            <p>To this he anſwered never a word, but was ſilent (1<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>) by acknowledging that I had Spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt her, but not to have her kept off, as Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> had charged me.</p>
            <p>Why did you then Speake againſt her, ſaid Mr <hi>Stucley?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwered becauſe ſhe had gone contrary to the <hi>law of Charity,</hi> in that ſhe did partake of the ordinance of the <hi>lords Supper</hi> with the <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> which we did not: If ſhe looked on this as her duty, ſhe could not but looke on the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect thereof, as our Sin, and ſo ſhe walked <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably:</hi> ſhe being in <hi>Societie</hi> with vs, and not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170370:23"/>
admoniſhing vs of our neglect, in ſuffering Sin uppon us.</p>
            <p>To this Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> replyed, what that lawe of Charitie was (for his part) he knew not, he knew noe ſuch law, Mr <hi>Roles</hi> ſaid It was a word haſtily ſpoken, and ſo it might be taken.</p>
            <p>After this Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> asked me, how I could go amon the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwered, that I looked on it as my dutie to wait upon God amongſt a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, reforming people.</p>
            <p>And then he told me, how that in my letter unto him, I had acknowledged that for a <hi>true Church,</hi> which I had formerly called <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwered, that I had called to mind ſo much as I could againſt my ſelfe, as to that particular of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo far as <hi>I</hi> could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member any ſuch expreſſions, I did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my evill therein, for which <hi>I</hi> had cauſe to be humbled: and withall that <hi>I</hi> did not <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> as from <hi>Babylon;</hi> that <hi>I</hi> looked upon them from whom vve <hi>ſeparated</hi> as true Churches in <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>worſhip,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> did not <hi>ſeparate</hi> from either of theſe, but only from their <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline:</hi> that the chiefe ground of my <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> vvas a <hi>Miſtake, I</hi> ſuppoſing that a Church <hi>rightly</hi> conſtituted muſt be joined together by an <hi>Explicite Covenant,</hi> vvhich <hi>I</hi> found to be othervviſe novv.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> vvas likevviſe queſtioned for oppoſing in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170370:23"/>
a publique meeting Mr. <hi>Stucley,</hi> as to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Paſtor</hi> at that time, vvhen they choſe him to be the <hi>Paſtor,</hi> and that in ſuch a <hi>Contentious</hi> manner, as to cauſe an hovver and halfe debate in the meeting. Mr. <hi>Whitehorne</hi> ſent them a paper, vvherein he profered to affirme vvith oath this charge.</p>
            <p>Which being denied by me, becauſe <hi>I</hi> knevv <hi>I</hi> vvas not preſent at the meeting at that time; Mr. <hi>Role</hi> and Mr. <hi>Slade</hi> ſaid they did believe that Mr. <hi>Whithorne</hi> vvas miſtaken (or to that effect) and Mr. <hi>Sprague</hi> expreſſely affirmed, that it vvas othervviſe then Mr. <hi>Whithorne</hi> had vvritten, for (ſaid he) vve did agree to conceale that meeting from her, leſt ſhe ſhould oppoſe him.</p>
            <p>I asked Mr. <hi>Roles</hi> and Mr. <hi>Slade</hi> where ever they knew me oppoſe Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> in a publique meeting? They ſaid no, they never knew it.</p>
            <p>Thus after they had ſpent ſome time in ſuch Cavills, Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> ſaid to me, you are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of a ſlip of your Tongue, of an Untruth.</p>
            <p>To which I replied, that this was a new thing, and deſired to know what ground he had for it.</p>
            <p>He anſwered here is Teſtimony, here are they who will witneſſe.</p>
            <p>I told him my witneſſe might be taken as ſoon as theirs, and had been formerly before theirs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170370:24"/>Mr. <hi>Rols</hi> then turning himſelfe towards Mr. <hi>Stucley,</hi> ſaid, that he believed there was never an untruth ſpoken, and it being things long before, and that every one ſpake as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred: and farther ſaid, that he wondred he made ſo much adoe about nothing.</p>
            <p>To which Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> replied, here is a <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> and an <hi>affirmative,</hi> and therefore a lye; although he never examined where the lye was.</p>
            <p>At the concluſion I told them that I ſhould come no more among them.</p>
            <p>This is the Subſtance of what I can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber concerning this daies diſcourſe, it being more then three yeares ſince. Whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares that I have juſt cauſe to charge the lye on themſelves.</p>
            <p>A few daies after they ſent for me againe, but I told the meſſenger, ſeeing they had ſo groſſely abuſed me, as to charge a lye upon me, I would come no more among them: that they were a people not to be truſted, and that I would be drawn in ſunder by wild horſes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then go unto them.</p>
            <p>However the ſame day I ſent unto Mr. <hi>Slade,</hi> one of the Officers, to know what they would have of me, who told me that they were very much troubled at my leaving them, and that they would look on my <hi>Returne</hi> as a <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170370:24"/>I deſired him to returne this as my anſwer unto them, viz. Let them ſtudy the Word, and convince me from the Word what is my dutie in ſuch a Caſe, and I would gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and willingly ſubmit to it, ſo unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling was I to offend them, yet to come any more among them I durſt not, becauſe of their former Carriage, neither was it (as I conceived) ſafe for me to adventure ſingly and without witneſſe among them, who were my <hi>accuſers, witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>judges.</hi> Since that day of the meeting aboveſaid I never ſpake with Mr. <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cley,</hi> though I deſired it ſeverall times.</p>
            <p>Some daies after Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> and Mr. <hi>Slade</hi> Officers, and a member with them came unto me, and (as they ſaid) expected Mr. <hi>Stucley's</hi> comeing likewiſe, but he came not.</p>
            <p>I then complained of their <hi>Carriage</hi> towards me, telling them how much I was troubled at it, and deſired them alſo to ſhew me from the word what they could expect, and then I ſhould ſubmit.</p>
            <p>One of them replied you muſt returne, and do otherwiſe, I anſwered, that I had too much to do with <hi>Separation</hi> already, and therefore ſhould not returne; then ſaid one of them, then they will never be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>As for Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> he told me, that my going away ſhould coſt me dearer then my coming in; and that they would proceed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170370:25"/>
to the order of the Churches: this was heard by another.</p>
            <p>I anſvvered, vvhatever I ſuffered by them, could not be ſo much as had ſuffered for them.</p>
            <p>After this others came to me, <hi>I</hi> told them <hi>I</hi> did expect to ſpeak vvith Mr. <hi>Stucley,</hi> that <hi>I</hi> might knovv vvhat he had againſt me, and that <hi>I</hi> vvas ready to ſubmit to the vvord, that they ſhould convince me thereby hovv <hi>I</hi> ought to be affected.</p>
            <p>Mris <hi>Roles</hi> alſo came unto me in vvay of a viſit, vvho deſired me to conſider vvhat a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour it vvould be unto the Church, if <hi>I</hi> left them: and as for vvhat you have at any time ſpoke unto them (ſaid ſhe) <hi>I</hi> believe it vvas in the uprightneſſe of your heart, and ſo doth my huſband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> told her that <hi>I</hi> did not juſtify my ſelfe in every particular as to the manner of it, ſaid ſhe, you ſpoile all in ſaying you vvill leave them, and if you do ſo, vvhat vvill they ſay of my <hi>Cozen Stucley?</hi> and what vvill they ſay of us? conſider, we are riſing, and more will come into us continually.</p>
            <p>And after this Mris. <hi>Stoneham</hi> came unto me, asking with teares in her eies, whether I would not returne, and whether ſhe was the cauſe of my going away.</p>
            <p>I demanded of her whether Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> knew of her coming? She anſwered, that ſhe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170370:25"/>
did not ſee him at her coming away. I then told her that it was reported by ſome of them, that they could not partake with me in ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances now:</p>
            <p>For my part (ſaid ſhe) I was never of that mind, neither do I know any who are, but on the contrary we are all much troubled that you will leave us.</p>
            <p>About two months after, <hi>Ezekiel Pace</hi> was ſent from Mr. <hi>Eveleigh,</hi> to tell me that I was <hi>ſuſpended</hi> by the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I told him that I had left their <hi>Society,</hi> and that I had no communion with them.</p>
            <p>He anſwered, they conceived that they could not otherwiſe diſcharge their dutie unto me, and as for what they had done, it was in order to my return.</p>
            <p>I replyed that my purpoſe was never to returne unto them.</p>
            <p>After I had made my Addreſſe to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the City, deſiring to be admitted into fellowſhip and communion with them in ordinances. Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> underſtanding thereof ſent Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> unto Mr. <hi>John Bartlet</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, to give him notice that they had ſeverall things againſt me: upon which it was by Mr. <hi>Bartlet</hi> deſired that they would produce their charge, which they promiſed to do, although it was long firſt, yet at length (after often deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it) a meeting was appointed at Mr. <hi>Fords</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170370:26"/>
houſe the Miniſter: Between Mr. <hi>Ford</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bartlet</hi> on the one ſide, and Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> and Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> on the other. At which mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I was preſent, there they did declare what they had againſt me, concerning Mris <hi>Eveleigh</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> where they charged me with an untruth. And the reſult of this <hi>conference</hi> was this, the <hi>Articles</hi> wherewith they charged me, being after ſerious <hi>Examination</hi> by all the miniſters of the City found partly doubtfull and proofeleſſe, and partly frivolous, I was ſhortly after (according as I deſired) received into Communion with them; and ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neer three yeares, till Mr. <hi>Stucley's</hi> Curſing began to make a noiſe in the world, which was neer three yeares after I deſerted them.</p>
            <p>Neer three years after my leaving of them, Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> acquainted me with a <hi>faſt</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their <hi>Excommunication.</hi> I then deſired that the buſineſſe might be brought to a new triall before the miniſters, whom they had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it formerly, and with whom I was in <hi>Communion,</hi> without whoſe advice I would do nothing.</p>
            <p>But this was not hearkned unto, they being (it ſeemes) reſolved on their worke of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> how cauſeleſſe and unjuſt ſoever.</p>
            <p>Let that letter that Mris. <hi>Allen</hi> and my ſelfe jointly ſubſcribed and ſent to Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> to be communicated to the Church, ſtand as a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170370:26"/>
witneſſe between us and them, to teſtifie to all the world how unjuſtly they charge us with <hi>Contumacy</hi> and refuſing of <hi>Admonition,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it evidently appeares that we honoured them ſo far as to receive their Summons, and to return them our <hi>Anſwer,</hi> wherein we did</p>
            <p n="1">1 Deſire a fair triall betvveen them and us before underſtanding and impartiall mrn.</p>
            <p n="2">2 We did profeſſe our deſire to ſubmit to the lavv and vvill of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> vvhen vve ſhould ſee reaſon from <hi>Scripture</hi> to Convince.</p>
            <p n="3">3 We did in the generall profeſſe our <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> for thoſe Evills that vve knevv our ſelves guilty of.</p>
            <p>Thus far vve condeſcended to them. And let the impartiall Reader judge vvhat they could expect more from us, vvho had upon <hi>Conſcientious principles</hi> withdrawne from <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with them, as Maſter <hi>Allen</hi> hath already declared of his wife; and my ſelfe having deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them neere three yeares before (being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the groundleſneſſe of <hi>ſeparation</hi> for ſeverall particulars I declared to the <hi>Elder;</hi> &amp; the cauſe of my withdrawing being not removed; but more offence being ſtill given by them, how could <hi>I</hi> acknowledge them ſo as to put my ſelfe upon their tryall. Beſides how could wee with ſafety put our ſelves on their triall, who were enraged with us ſince we left them; which they diſcovered by their <hi>Calumniating</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faming</hi> of us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170370:27"/>Beſides we having been in fellowſhip with the Lords people in other congregations; my ſelfe ſeverall yeares, and Mris. <hi>Allen</hi> for ſome time, we being ſo aſperſed by them as we were, how could we cleer our ſelves, ſo as to ſatisfie them that we were in Communion with (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a tryall) ſo as that they might not ſuffer by us; for what we were aſperſed with, did in ſome manner reflect upon them, who had received us into fellowſhip with them.</p>
            <p>And whereas Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> in his book Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>(Manifeſt Truth)</hi> pag. 22. pretends that it robbes particular Churches of that power and authority which Chriſt hath intruſted them with, of Trying and cenſuring their own <hi>delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent members</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> This is nothing to the purpoſe, we were not their members, but reall members of ſome other congregations. If they have power to cenſure their own <hi>delinquent members,</hi> we doe not hinder them from exerciſing their power. But have they therefore power to Cenſure the <hi>members</hi> of other Churches? we had withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from <hi>Communion</hi> with them, and they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not ſatisfied us ſo as to remove the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our leaving them.</p>
            <p>May he not therefore reflect upon himſelfe, who hath contrary to his own profeſſed princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples robbed the Church of their power, and of their <hi>members</hi> in <hi>Cenſuring</hi> of us, without the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170370:27"/>
               <hi>Approbation</hi> of thoſe <hi>miniſters</hi> and <hi>congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> to which we ſtood reiared? May we not therefore aske him, who gave you this <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of lording it over <hi>Churches</hi> and their <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> without their Counſell or conſent? Is not this practice of his too much like thoſe that the Apoſtle foretells of <hi>Acts</hi> 20.24. <hi>For I know this that after my departure ſhall grievous wolves en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in among you, not ſparing the flock,</hi> and our Saviour tells us <hi>there are wolves in ſheeps-cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ye ſhall know them by their fruits, Matth,</hi> 7.15, 16. Beſides, let it be conſidered, in denying of us this liberty to have a fair Triall, hath he not hereby denyed <hi>Communion of Churches,</hi> he being ſince deſired ſeverall times by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall miniſters of the City, that the buſineſſe might be brought to a Triall, they judging it unreaſonable that we ſhould be excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them, untill the cauſe be clearly proved, and we be permitted to Anſwer for our ſelves. But this he hath evaded for ſeverall months, and in ſtead thereof takes liberty to preach and print what he pleaſeth of us, that ſo he may render our names and perſons odious to them that know us not.</p>
            <p>And for farther Anſwer to him in that he pretends that it robs the <hi>Church</hi> of the power that Chriſt hath given &amp;c. It being a point of <hi>controverſie</hi> I ſhall leave it to the learned. Let him conſult the Judgments of thoſe that are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170370:28"/>
for the <hi>Congregationall way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Apologeticall Narration</hi> preſented to the houſe of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſubſcribed by T.G. P. N. S.S. I.B. W.B. in anſwer to this objection, viz. That in ſuch a <hi>congregationall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> thus entire within it ſelfe, there is not allowed ſufficient Remedy for miſcarriages or wrongfull ſentences, or perſons injured there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, no Room for complaints, no powerfull or effectuall means to reduce a <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Churches</hi> that fall into hereſie, or ſchiſme; but every one is left, and may take liberty, without controle <hi>to do what is good in their owne eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. We could not but judge it a ſafe, &amp; an allowed way to retaine th Government of our ſeverall <hi>Congregations</hi> for matter of <hi>diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> within themſelves, &amp;c. yet not claiming to our ſelves an <hi>independent power</hi> in every <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> to give account, or be ſubject to none others, but onely a full and entire power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat within our ſelves, untill we ſhould be chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged to erre groſly: ſuch as <hi>Corporations</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, who have the power and priviledge to paſſe ſentence for life and death within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and yet are accountable to the State they live in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. An inſtance they give of their owne practice in a buſineſſe of this nature of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi> wherewith ſome <hi>Churches</hi> were offended.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170370:28"/>In this Caſe our <hi>Churches</hi> did mutually and univerſally acknowledge and ſubmit to this as a Sacred and undoubted Principle and ſupreme Law to be obſerved among all Churches. That as by vertue of that <hi>Apoſtolicall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> Churches as well as particular men are bound to give no offence, neither to <hi>Jew</hi> or <hi>Gentile,</hi> nor the Churches of God they live amongſt: ſo that in all caſes of ſuch offences or difference, by the obligation of the <hi>common law of Communion of Churches,</hi> and for the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the glory of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon they hold forth, the Church or Churches challenged to offend or differ are to ſubmit themſelves, upon the challenge of the offence or complaint of the perſon wronged, to the moſt full and open triall and examination by other neighbour churches offended thereat, of what ever hath given the offence. And farther that by vertue of the ſame and like law of not partaking of other mens ſins, the Churches offended may &amp; ought (upon the Impenitency of thoſe Churches perſiſting in their error and miſcarriage) to pronounce that heavy ſentence againſt them of withdrawing and renouncing all Chriſtian Communion with them, untill they do repent. And farther, to declare and proteſt this, with the cauſes thereof to all other Churches of Chriſt that they might do the like.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170370:29"/>Pag. 21. It was openly and publiquely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in a ſpeech, that was the Preface to that diſcuſſion, to this effect. That it was the moſt abhorred <hi>Maxime</hi> that any <hi>Religion</hi> hath ever made Profeſſion of, and therefore of all other the moſt contradictory and diſhonourable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that of <hi>Chriſtianity, That a ſingle and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Society within themſelves ſhould farther ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate unto themſelves an Exemption from give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing account, or being Cenſureable by any other, either Chriſtian magiſtrate above them; or neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Churches about them.</hi> So farr (ſay they) were our Iudgements, from that Independent liberty, that is imputed to us.</p>
            <p>So Mr <hi>Borroughs,</hi> heart diviſion <hi>p.</hi> 43. where he ſayes, Thoſe in the <hi>Congregationall way</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that they are bound in <hi>conſcience,</hi> to give account of their wayes to the Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, or to any other who ſhall require it, this, not in an <hi>Arbitrary way,</hi> but as a duty they owe to God and man.</p>
            <p>Reader, here you ſee how wide and diſſonant, the judgements of thoſe (more) learned of the <hi>Congregationall way</hi> are from the practice and proceedings of Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> &amp; his Church: Thoſe of that way acknowledging, but hee denying, ſubmiſſion to any <hi>examination,</hi> or <hi>triall</hi> by neighbour Churches, and hee and his Church claiming an <hi>Independent</hi> power, or liberty to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170370:29"/>
give no account, or be ſubject to no others, though accuſed and challenged for erring groſly in point of their Arbitrary unjuſt proceedings againſt us, which is plainly manifeſted in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Allen's</hi> booke called <hi>(Truths manifeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived)</hi> and will farther appeare in my enſuing Vindication, to which I haſten; This being (to my beſt remembrance) a true Relation of what paſſed between us, untill the <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="vindication">
               <head>THE <hi>VINDICATION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY that which hath been ſaid in my <hi>Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative,</hi> it is manifeſt that I was never queſtioned, much leſſe admoniſhed for <hi>lying,</hi> untill my coming off from them, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170370:30"/>
they never accounted me (whiles I was with them) ſuch a vile perſon as now by their <hi>ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous pamphlets</hi> they endeavour to make the world believe me to be: and here I cannot but wonder at Mr <hi>Mall,</hi> that he, being a ſtranger to me, and altogether ignorant of my manner of life and converſation, ſhould yet be ſo raſh and inconſiderate, as meerly upon <hi>reports</hi> to defame me in <hi>Print,</hi> for which he is bound in conſcience as he is a <hi>Miniſter</hi> (if he be one) a Chriſtian, yea, as he is a man, to give the Church of God, mee, and the world, ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>The Notes, (ſaith he in his <hi>Epiſtle to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>) of Mr <hi>Stucleys Sermon,</hi> I am glad I took in ſhort hand from his mouth, or otherwiſe thou mighteſt never have ſeen a true <hi>Copy</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>Surely, if the <hi>Copy</hi> do agree with the <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> (which ſome queſtion) I ſhall be ſo bold to affirme of both that they exceedingly diſagree with the <hi>Truth,</hi> in laying thoſe <hi>Crimes</hi> to my charge which they are never able to prove, as will ſufficiently (I beleive) appeare in theſe my following <hi>Anſwers</hi> to their Severall <hi>Articles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall begin with that of <hi>lying,</hi> it being that which my accuſer begins and almoſt ends with, which he in many places of his book mentions with a great deale of pretended <hi>zeale</hi> and <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> which he indeavours to equall with the ſin of <hi>Inceſt,</hi> which he ſaith is a fault deteſtable to the very <hi>heathens.</hi> Some of them, this is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170370:30"/>
the <hi>Cryme</hi> which he and his party eſpecially charge me with both in <hi>Citie</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> crying out every where, I am a lyar, yea an egregious one, and therefore juſtly <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated,</hi> This is in fine, the Article on which the whole <hi>charge</hi> depends.</p>
               <p>Before I come to the <hi>Charge</hi> it ſelfe in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, I ſhall crave leave to ſpeake ſomething in the generall concerning the apprehenſion I have of this <hi>Sin,</hi> as alſo ſomewhat concerning Maſter <hi>Stucleys</hi> practice in reference unto it, whereby it will be evident, both how improbable it is that I ſhould be ſuch an <hi>Egregious lyer,</hi> as hee hath made mee in his booke, and alſo how unlikely it is, that hee ſhould be ſo <hi>zealouſly</hi> affected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>lying</hi> as he therein pretends.</p>
               <p>For the firſt of theſe. <hi>Lying</hi> is that <hi>Sin,</hi> which my <hi>Parents</hi> from time to time, ſo repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto me in the ſeverall aggravations and deformities thereof, as that I alwaies (ſince I came to yeares of diſcretion) abhorred, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted it, both in my ſelfe and others.</p>
               <p>I account a <hi>lyar</hi> unfit not onely for <hi>Chriſtian Communion,</hi> but alſo <hi>civill Commerce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the word, and my own ſadd experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>I</hi> finde it to be an <hi>hereditary evill</hi> in all the ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam: That the heart is deceitfull and deſperately wicked above all things, who can know it?</hi> That there is a way
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170370:31"/>
of <hi>lying</hi> in the beſt of men by nature, in this ſenſe, <hi>let God be true, and every man a lyer;</hi> The guile, deceipt, falſhood, and hypocriſy which is in the heart, is that which is a chiefe part and member of the <hi>bodie of death,</hi> and that which makes it out of meaſure, ſinfull, and an intollerable burthen to be borne.</p>
               <p>As to the practice of this <hi>ſin, I</hi> do believe that it is not conſiſtent with the worke of grace, That he which lives in the practice thereof, is not a <hi>member</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> but a <hi>limbe</hi> of the <hi>divell,</hi> it is ſo contrary to the God of truth, ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie unto Chriſt, who is <hi>the Truth,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie unto <hi>the Spirit of Truth,</hi> and ſo contrary unto the work of <hi>Regeneration,</hi> as I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ſuch a ſoule as lives in the practice thereof, or hath ſlight thoughts of it, was ever begotten againe by <hi>the word of Truth;</hi> neither is it (I conceive) poſſible for ſuch a one to enjoy comfortable communion with God.</p>
               <p>I looke on it as a <hi>diſtinguiſhing Character,</hi> whereby the Children of God are known from the children of the divel, <hi>The Remnant of Iſrael ſhall not doe iniquity, nor ſpeak lies, neither ſhall a deceitfull tongue be found in their mouthes. Lyers</hi> are excluded from the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> that cometh down from God out of heaven, whoſoever loveth and maketh a lie is in the number of thoſe who are without: The hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fortie and four thouſand that ſtand with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170370:31"/>
the <hi>Lambe</hi> on <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> having his fathers name written on their foreheads, which follow the <hi>lambe</hi> whereſoever he goeth, which were redeemed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among men, being the <hi>firſt-fruits</hi> unto God and to the <hi>lambe,</hi> in their mouth was found no <hi>Guile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I hope through <hi>grace</hi> in ſome meaſure I can ſay, That I have ſeen ſuch a deſireable beauty in <hi>Truth,</hi> as with <hi>David</hi> to hate and abhorre <hi>lying,</hi> &amp; whatſoever is contrary unto <hi>truth,</hi> guile, deceit, hypocriſie, falſhood, a falſe heart, falſe wayes, falſe doctrines, though under never ſo faire pretences, when once they are throughly diſcovered.</p>
               <p>And as to my <hi>practice,</hi> as I deſire to lay aſide every weight that preſſeth down, and the <hi>Sin that doth ſo eaſily beſet me,</hi> So is it my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in all my approaches unto the <hi>Throne of Grace,</hi> the word &amp; ordinances, to obtain ſtrength for the purging out more &amp; more of the Guile, hypocriſie, falſhood, and deceit that is in my heart, and is ſtill diſcovering it ſelfe before the Lord, and ready to break out on all occaſions, which doth continually adminiſter matter of <hi>lamentation</hi> unto me.</p>
               <p>And becauſe I find by ſad <hi>experience</hi> that this <hi>body of death</hi> doth not lie idle, but is ſtill bringing forth fruit unto death; and being not willing to reſt in my own <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> conſidering often that of <hi>Solomon, he that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170370:32"/>
truſteth his own heart is a fool:</hi> and fearing alſo leſt through <hi>corruption</hi> I might forget the miſcarriages laid to my charge (ſome yeares being expired ere ever I was queſtioned for them) or put them off, I did earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire againe and again to ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe, that I might know his <hi>grounds</hi> in charging me with <hi>lying,</hi> but all to no purpoſe; he could not be ſpoken with.</p>
               <p>And ſo alſo ſince the <hi>Excommunication</hi> did I write unto him to know the particulars whereof I am accuſed in reference to <hi>lying,</hi> that ſo I might accordingly either <hi>juſtifie</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne</hi> my ſelfe. But he in ſtead of ſatisfying my juſt and reaſonable demand, moſt imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and prelatically ſends me a letter full of bitter <hi>Calumniations,</hi> accuſing me to be a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, dividing,</hi> and <hi>lying Spirit,</hi> without ſo much as naming any particulars.</p>
               <p>As to the Second, I might referre the <hi>Reader</hi> for proof hereof to his <hi>practice.</hi> It will be found upon triall that he is not of <hi>Davids</hi> minde in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.7. to <hi>Baniſh</hi> from his houſe and ſight, every one that worketh deceit and telleth lies; and though he pretend to baniſh mee (upon that account) from his <hi>ſociety</hi> and <hi>fellowſhip,</hi> yet he never queſtioned me for lying, untill I departed from him, untill I ſent him word that I would come no more among them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170370:32"/>When he and Maſter <hi>Eveleigh</hi> accuſed me to Maſter <hi>Forde,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Bartlet</hi> of <hi>lying,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Forde</hi> asked him whether he had ever ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed me for thoſe things whereof he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed me, To which he anſwered that he had not been faithfull unto me, and that I had told him of it my ſelfe, And Maſter <hi>Eveleigh</hi> added, That they had much a doe to pleaſe me.</p>
               <p>Had I continued with them I ſhould, without doubt, notwithſtanding all thoſe <hi>lyes</hi> I am now accuſed of; have been as favorably dealt with, as two other of their <hi>members,</hi> who were notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly guilty of <hi>lyeing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the firſt of them, it was briefly thus; we having beene enjoyned <hi>Secreſie</hi> by Mr <hi>Stucley,</hi> there was notwithſtanding ſomewhat of our <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conferences</hi> divulged and made knowne.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the next meeting every one was examined, and charged in a ſolemne manner to declare whether they knew who it was that had revealed it: To which a negative anſwer was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by every one, and when I deſired Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Stucley</hi> to ſearch after it more narrowly, and preſſe it more cloſely upon them, that the <hi>Lyar</hi> might be found out, he put mee off with this, that it had beene ſo in another Church, and though he knew who it was afterward (as I am informed) yet the party was never admoniſhed at any of our meetings.</p>
               <p>Here was (to be ſure) a <hi>negative</hi> and an <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170370:33"/>
a breach of promiſe, and then a deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that which was freſh in memory and (which is more) the words ſpoken in prvitae be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene our ſelves were miſ-reported, and yet Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> could quietly paſſe it over.</p>
               <p>The other is <hi>John Whitehorne,</hi> who offered to affirme with oath, that which was by two or three of the members preſently contradicted; and yet Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> hath beene ſo farre from ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing him for it, as that I heare he is now become an Elder.</p>
               <p>By all which it is more then probable, that there is little of truth to be expected in his <hi>lying charge,</hi> which he expreſſeth in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charge.</hi> As for Mris <hi>Parr</hi> ſhe is accuſed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g other things for <hi>lying</hi> more than three times ſufficiently proved, in <hi>pag.</hi> 18. of his booke publiſhed by Mr <hi>Mall.</hi> But when ſhe was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Church admonition concerning ſeverall things, ſhe was found tripping very much in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to her Tongue, and <hi>lying egregiouſly,</hi> ſo that the <hi>whole Church</hi> could bear witneſs againſt her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol:</hi> If this <hi>Charge</hi> be throughly ſifted, it will be found faulty more wayes then one, and ſo <hi>egregiouſly tripping,</hi> and <hi>halting,</hi> as that every unbyaſſed Reader may witneſſe againſt it. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. It runs altogether in the generall, in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming mee to be under <hi>Church admonition,</hi> for ſeverall things, without naming any one: And
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170370:33"/>
then in accuſeing mee only of <hi>lying</hi> in generall, without inſtancing in ſo much as one particular, whereby others are poſſeſſed with a <hi>prejudice</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, and my ſelfe diſenabled to alleadge any thing in mine owne <hi>defence,</hi> not knowing how the particulars will be framed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, it confidently aſſerts me guilty of <hi>lying</hi> more then three times ſufficiently proved, and that ſo <hi>egregiouſly,</hi> as all <hi>the Church could witneſſe againſt mee;</hi> when as one of their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall <hi>members</hi> declared (at that time when I was accuſed of Tripping) in their meeting that hee thought there was never an untruth ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but that every one ſpake as they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly and laſtly, it ſayes, I was under Church admonition for ſeverall things.</p>
               <p>What hee meaneth by <hi>Church admonition</hi> I ſcarce underſtand; if by <hi>Church admonition</hi> hee meanes that diſcourſe which wee had together at the very time (being ten dayes after I left them, when as he ſaith, I was found tripping) I ſay it was no <hi>admonition</hi> (as I conceived) but onely an <hi>examination,</hi> as appeares in my <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> If he would inſinuate thereby that I was under <hi>Church admonition</hi> before that time. Then I ſay it could be but for one thing onely which is omitted; neither is there any mention made of it throughout the whole booke; And that was my hearing Mr <hi>Forde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170370:34"/>Its true Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> told me, my ſpeaking was diſreliſhed, whereupon I left that practice neere two yeares before I left them; Its true likewiſe that the Elder accuſed mee of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon which I made my appeale unto the <hi>Church,</hi> who with one conſent acquitted me of that charge,</p>
               <p>The Elder alſo accuſed me of <hi>cenſoriouſnes</hi> for oppoſing <hi>(Ganicle)</hi> who not longe after tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Quaker,</hi> and therby cleered me of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; ſo that I could not be at this time, when as they ſay I lyed ſo egregiouſly, under <hi>church admonition</hi> for either of theſe,</p>
               <p>And as for any other things I cannot reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber any that they did ever manifeſt the leaſt diſlike of, unleſſe my practice of hearing Mr <hi>Forde,</hi> (which is the thing (not things) for which I was under <hi>Church admonition</hi>) the thing which hath occaſioned all this trouble; and for which, (as Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> in a letter formerly threatned) they have proceeded to <hi>cenſure</hi> mee, though it be daubed over with lying &amp; other forged crimes.</p>
               <p>This practice of hearing Mr <hi>Forde</hi> was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted mee, or at the leaſt winked at by them, ſo long as I had a friend that might pleaſure them in the City and in the Parliament—. Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> preſently upon his being an <hi>Officer,</hi> told mee that he did expect I ſhould heare him, and no other, to which I preſently replyed, that it would be hard for mee to leave that Miniſtry
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170370:34"/>
which the Lord had made ſo profitable unto mee, and withall gave him my grounds for that practice. At length at the cloſe of our diſcourſe, he ſaid, we ſhould not diſagree about it, and yet afterwards Maſter <hi>Stoneham</hi> was put upon it to preach and pray againſt mee for this practice.</p>
               <p>To take mee off from this practice alſo was Mr <hi>Sprague</hi> ſent unto me, by Mr <hi>Stoneham:</hi> the very ſame day at the meeting the Elder told me, they had two things againſt me, one was <hi>Contention,</hi> the other my hearing Mr <hi>Forde,</hi> which the <hi>Church</hi> neither could nor would bear: the Elder the next day after the buſineſſe of <hi>contention</hi> was ended, told mee that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt mee but my hearing Mr <hi>Forde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Slade</hi> alſo, and Mr <hi>Rolls</hi> came to mee as meſſengers from the <hi>Church</hi> (as they ſaid) to admoniſh me in particular of hearing Mr <hi>Forde:</hi> Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe wrote me two long letters, about this very thing, &amp; in one of them threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>cenſure</hi> mee for it: they kept a faſt for this very particular the 24. of <hi>February</hi> 1654.</p>
               <p>They omitted the adminiſtration of the Lords Supper for this reaſon (as Mr <hi>Raddon</hi> told me) yea Mr <hi>Stoneham</hi> ſaid, that if I would not ſit downe under his Miniſtry, he would be no Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer unto mee.</p>
               <p>When I was deſired afterwards to forbeare coming to the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> without giving any other reaſon then this; That ſome body did
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170370:35"/>
deſire me to forbeare (who this ſomebody was I could never learne) I went forthwith to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall members, to know what they had againſt mee, who anſwered, they had nothing, but my going to heare others, which practice (they ſaid) was deſtructive to the Church. By all which it is manifeſt that this was the onely thing they had againſt mee, untill I had left them, and yet this is omitted, and other things are pretended. Let all the world judge whether this be not <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine ſubtilty:</hi> As to this charge of (lying) I ſhall deſire the Reader to conſider farther theſe three or fower particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The time when they found me Tripping, (as he ſaith) it was after I had left them. Before I had ſent them word that I was reſolved to withdraw from their <hi>Society</hi> I was never queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned for a lye: what doth this imply, but that they reſolved my going off ſhould coſt mee dearer then my coming in among them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Elder Mr <hi>Eveleighs</hi> threatning.</p>
               <p>Again, it was at that time when I went to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>love,</hi> in <hi>the ſimplicity of my heart,</hi> to give them <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> why I left them, as I did at the firſt why <hi>I</hi> aſſociated my ſelfe with them; thinking as little to be charged with lying, as with theft, murder, or other ſins not to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med among <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And here <hi>I</hi> cannot but commend Mris <hi>Allen</hi> her diſcretion, in refuſing to adventure her ſelf ſingly among them, which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170370:35"/>
had ſhe done, they would have made her as great a lyer, as my ſelfe, thereby Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> would have been freed from the trouble of fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming two indifferent bills of indictment againſt us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, the matters about which they examined me at that time were ſuch as had been done and paſt long before, ſome yeares: ſo that if through weakneſſe of memory, my tongue had tripped, how will it follow hence that <hi>I</hi> lyed ſo <hi>egregiouſly</hi> as to deſerve <hi>Excommunication?</hi> How could they be ſure that <hi>I</hi> made a lye, though <hi>I</hi> had ſpoken an untruth, unleſſe they knew certainly, that <hi>I</hi> ſpake againſt my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>I</hi> did in my anſwers to their fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous and cavilling queſtions inſert by way of <hi>caution (viz.) as I remember: according to my beſt remembrance, &amp;c.</hi> which might have <hi>ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> them, as it did M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Rolls</hi> at that time, had they not beene fully bent to ſlander mee for leaving them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fowerthly, <hi>I</hi> was onely accuſed, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, of lying: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley</hi> ſaid, here are they who will witneſſe, but yet they did not witneſſe any particular, that I abſolutely denied, except <hi>John Whitehorne,</hi> whoſe teſtimony (though he offered to confirme it with oath) was preſently contradicted by another of their members. Why did not M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley</hi> according to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170370:36"/>
even of heatheniſh Romans, <hi>Act.</hi> 25.16. (who in this ſhew the worke of <hi>the Law written in their hearts</hi>) require as an Officer, every one to ſpeake out what they had to ſay againſt me? was it for feare leſt they ſhould be found <hi>Trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi> as <hi>John Whitehorne</hi> was? I appeale to all impartiall Readers, whether it be not a moſt <hi>unrighteous judgement</hi> thus to condemne mee without being convicted, yea when I was cleared by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Rolls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And farther let it be conſidered that I was ſo farre acquitted by the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of this <hi>City,</hi> as that they gave mee the right hand of fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, notwithſtanding their <hi>impeachments,</hi> which I believe they are ready to witneſſe unto the Church, of God when it ſhall be required of them. This may ſuffice to be ſpoken in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the charge of <hi>lying</hi> in the generall.</p>
               <p>I ſhall in the next place proceed to Anſwer the Particulars of this <hi>lying Charge,</hi> as I find them laid down by Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> in another Pamphlet of his, Intituled <hi>Manifeſt Truth.</hi> Being an <hi>Angry Anſwer</hi> to Mr. <hi>Toby Allein,</hi> in in which he hath unboſomed and diſcovered himſelfe more fully then in Mr. <hi>Mall's</hi> Book. In pag. 41. and ſo onwards, he reduceth the grounds of my <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> to three heads, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiouſneſſe, Cenſoriouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Lying,</hi> each of which he inſtanceth in ſeverall particulars. The laſt of theſe I ſhall begin with, and anſwer in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170370:36"/>
the firſt place, which I ſhall do, having briefly conſidered what he ſaith concerning the grounds of my <hi>Suſpenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to that <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> that <hi>Ezekiel Pace</hi> gave me notice of, I ſay that it was neer two months after I had left them, after I was withdrawen from their <hi>communion;</hi> which <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> (as the meſſenger ſaid) was in order to my <hi>returne.</hi> By which I gather that the chiefe ground thereof was my going away: and that it is ſo, as alſo their <hi>Excommunication,</hi> almoſt three yeares after, will be manifeſted fully by my following anſwer; wherein I ſhall ſhew that they had no ground at all to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> or <hi>excommunicate</hi> me for any of thoſe three particulars mentioned by Mr. <hi>Stucley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And firſt of <hi>lying,</hi> which in pag. 44, 45. he endeavours to prove in ſix particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 1. She affirmed, that ſhe alwaies acknowledged <hi>Presbyterian Churches</hi> to be <hi>true Churches</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> and that it was hard for her to <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in diſtinguiſhing ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; whereas ſhe excepted againſt Mr. <hi>Toby Allein,</hi> for having his child Baptized by Mr. <hi>Ford,</hi> and oppoſed his admiſſion on that ground: there were 4 witneſſes to this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolut.</hi> This inſtance hath more of <hi>Craft</hi> (if I underſtand it) then either truth or reaſon, and may very well (I think) anſwer it ſelfe.
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170370:37"/>
I am here brought in oppoſing Mr. <hi>Allens ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion,</hi> and in other pages of his book he ſaith Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> conſented to my <hi>ſuſpenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> denies the one, ſo do <hi>I</hi> the other. But ſuppoſe I ſhould have done it, they all know it was my judgment and my practice at that time: where is the lye?</p>
               <p>I told them it was very hard for mee to <hi>ſeparate</hi> in diſtinguiſhing Ordinances. And they may remember the ſame time I told them alſo what was my ground why I did <hi>ſeparate:</hi> what can be gathered hence, but that I did that which was very hard for me to do, <hi>ſeparate</hi> in diſtinguiſhing Ordinances, and diſlike Mr. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> becauſe he was not of the ſame mind?</p>
               <p>But I am very much diſſatisfied and offended with this <hi>charge,</hi> becauſe it doth differ from the <hi>charge</hi> which I was charged with by them, which was this, namely for ſpeaking againſt Mr <hi>Allen,</hi> becauſe he did partake of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the <hi>Lords ſupper</hi> with the <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this <hi>I</hi> denied; my reaſon was, becauſe <hi>I</hi> had never heard at that time, that Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> did partake with the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; its now Seaven yeares ſince.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 2. She affirmed that ſhe never oppoſed Mris <hi>Dorothy Eveleighs</hi> admiſſion, but was for it, whereas the generality of the then members of the Church witneſſed, that a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170370:37"/>
long time ſhe openly contended againſt it to the griefe of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolut.</hi> 1. I have marveild many times why they ſhould queſtion me about oppoſing of her, who was long before in her grave, and with whom <hi>I</hi> had loving and <hi>Chriſtian converſe</hi> to her dying day.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, That <hi>I</hi> affirmed that <hi>I</hi> never ſpake againſt her is falſe, neither could <hi>I</hi> get any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by it, ſeeing others of the Church did the like, in whom it was not lookt upon as an evill. <hi>I</hi> might ſay more, but that <hi>I</hi> am unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to rake in the aſhes of the dead.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, <hi>I</hi> gave Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> a Reaſon why <hi>I</hi> ſpake againſt her at the firſt, (which he himſelfe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions pag. 43. in the 4th. particular of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi>) not to have her kept off, but that ſhe might acknowledge her ſin in breaking the law of Charity &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>, That <hi>I</hi> did ſpeak for her <hi>admiſsion,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> himſele witneſſed it to Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> in his own houſe, and alſo another of their members E.B. hath (as ſhe told me) declared unto them that it was <hi>I</hi> who prevailed with her to conſent unto the admiſſion of Mris <hi>Dorothie Eveleigh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 3. She denied that ſhe ever called the <hi>Preſbyterian Churches</hi> by the name of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> whereas moſt of the Church witneſſed that ſhe had often ſo called them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170370:38"/>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> What I anſwered Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> when he did in a manner reprove me for acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to be a <hi>true Church,</hi> which formerly I had called <hi>Babylon,</hi> appeares in the Narrative. To which I ſhall farther adde</p>
               <p n="1">1 Suppoſe it were true, that I had in the heat of <hi>Contention</hi> at our firſt <hi>ſeparation</hi> vented ſome raſh and inconſiderate expreſſions in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the <hi>Presbyterian Churches,</hi> or the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> themſelves, yet it ill becomes Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> and the reſt to be my accuſers, who continue in the ſame practice; in judging me for this, they do but condemne themſelves, according to that of the Apoſtle <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. Why do they cenſure me now for this, ſeeing I am not guilty of it at preſent? why did not they admoniſh me for it formerly, when I was with them?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Would they even now be ſo faithfull unto me, as to name any particular time, place, or other circumſtance that might bring ſuch expreſſions to my remembrance, they ſhould find me as ready to condemne my ſelfe, as they are to accuſe me, if done in an orderly manner.</p>
               <p n="3">(3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>) It may be that which occaſioned this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, was my mentioning of <hi>Babylons brats,</hi> at the time when I ſpake my <hi>Experiences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I did then declare how hard it was for me to <hi>Separate</hi> from thoſe who were godly, and whoſe miniſtry had bin ſo profitable unto me: But
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170370:38"/>
when I conſidered the command of god, <hi>Touch noe uncleane thing, and I will receive you. &amp;c.</hi> I conceived it did ſufficiently warrant our <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perating</hi> from them: And farther I declared that there were many litle ones, <hi>Babyloniſh Brats,</hi> which muſt be daſht againſt the ſtones, which (I then told them) I did underſtand of things, not perſons. But they, many of them, being newly crept into a <hi>forme of godlines,</hi> were ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of that <hi>diſtinction,</hi> as what I ſpake of things, they interpreted of perſons; which was ſo farr from my thoughts, as that when I began to read the Booke Intituled, <hi>(one blowe more to Babylon.) I</hi> lay'd it aſide, as not being able to Cloſe with the Author thereof, becauſe of his many <hi>Reflections</hi> therein, though (as they all know) <hi>I</hi> had a high eſteme of him, and did not uſe to ſlight him.</p>
               <p n="4">(4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>) When <hi>I</hi> did at any time afterward name <hi>Babylon, I</hi> never meant it but of <hi>Babylon</hi> in the <hi>Myſtery,</hi> conſiſting either in the joyning of mens <hi>Inventions</hi> with Chriſts inſtitutions; or in preſſing of things indifferent upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as neceſſary; or in the ſetting up of mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the Ordinances of Chriſt, So far as <hi>I</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended any of theſe, <hi>I</hi> did declare againſt them: And for theſe very things doe <hi>I</hi> now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt that <hi>Congregation</hi> from which <hi>I</hi> have departed, which <hi>I</hi> little thought at firſt would have bin found amongſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170370:39"/>
                  <hi>Jnſtance.</hi> 4. She denied that ever ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to have Mr <hi>Stoneham</hi> paſtor, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her owne hand were theſe words, <hi>J never laboured to bring him to that office;</hi> whereas the contrary was witneſſed by three perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſolut.</hi> What I affirmed in my letter I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be truth, neither have I reaſon to think the contrary: if it were as Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> ſayth, More then three would have been able to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it: 'tis true, he being an ancient <hi>non confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,</hi> and very ſenſible of the evils under which the Church of God did formerly groane, I had a good eſteeme of him; but that I laboured to have him Paſtor, will never (I believe) be clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved, yea two or three of the chiefeſt of them, did witneſſe in the meeting, that they never heard mee ſpeake for him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jnſtance</hi> 5. She affirmed that ſhe never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitted by Mr <hi>Stonehams</hi> preachings, and never approved his Miniſtry, the contrary hereunto was witneſſed by three perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> What I affirmed concerning Mr <hi>Stone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was in a letter in theſe words, <hi>(viz.) As for M.</hi> Stonehams <hi>preachings, J have had little benefit by it, but J have imputed it to my owne dulneſſe in hearing, and did hope that when J was better acquainted with his method in teaching J ſhould profit more by it:</hi> they that vvitneſſe other then this vvitneſſe a lie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jnſtance</hi> 6. Shee denyeth in a letter, That
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170370:39"/>
ſhee ſuſpected thoſe that had Kindred and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations among the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> whereas many vvitneſſed the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> 1. If the contrary vvere true, then I muſt have ſuſpected my ſelfe having Kindred and acquaintance that vvere <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> vvith who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had daily <hi>ſocietie,</hi> &amp; intimate <hi>communion,</hi> and vvhom I did highly honour, for the image of God ſhining in them; though our judgments differed.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Let them ſhew me the perſons vvhom I ſuſpected, and I vvill ſhew other grounds of my ſuſpicion.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. They themſelves queſtioned me for my affections to thoſe of different judgements, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and therefore I cannot but vvonder, that they ſhould dare to charge mee vvith this.</p>
               <p>This may (I hope) ſuffice vvith all judicious and impartiall <hi>Readers,</hi> for the vviping off that filth, vvhich they flung after mee at my leaving them, in reference to <hi>lying,</hi> one of thoſe three generalls to vvhich he reduced the ground of my <hi>Suſpenſion;</hi> the other two are <hi>contentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>cenſoriouſneſſe,</hi> ſo he is pleaſed to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, Love and Faithfulneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Contention.</hi> The firſt of theſe <hi>(Contention)</hi> he ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 41. in his Anſwer to Mr <hi>Toby Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> vvas proved by many vvitneſſes in ſix par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170370:40"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As to this <hi>I</hi> anſvver, that <hi>I</hi> vvas cleared by the vvhole Church of this <hi>Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (as in my narrative) vvhich all of them can vvitneſſe if they vvill; ſince that time none of them ever undertook to prove it to my face.</p>
               <p>I was ſo far from delighting in <hi>Contention,</hi> as that I complained of it to Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> ſeverall times, and alſo in a letter I told him plainly, that I was not able to live in the fire of <hi>Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> nor ſit down under a <hi>miniſtry</hi> that I could not profit by, and therefore I ſhould willingly withdraw from them; which I did accordingly for this and other reaſons, &amp; therefore he hath little reaſon to accuſe me of <hi>Contention.</hi> But he ſaith it was proved in theſe particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 1. In very many, if not in moſt of thoſe debates which have been in the Church ſince our firſt coming together, ſhe hath been uſually ſilent, untill the <hi>Church</hi> have been rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to come to ſome determination, or had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and then ſhe would object againſt what ſhe perceived was the Judgment of the <hi>Church,</hi> and purſued it with much <hi>violence.</hi> This the generality of the then <hi>Church</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. Was I ſilent till the laſt? why may not <hi>Elihu's</hi> Apologie be mine? <hi>Job.</hi> 32.4, 5, 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p n="2">2 My <hi>Aſſent</hi> was required to their <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations,</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170370:40"/>
and therefore it was very fit I ſhould know what ground there was for them; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering that the <hi>then Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> the generality of them were <hi>novices</hi> in <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and very weak in the firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; ſo unacquainted with the Rule, as that they knew not how to behave themſelves in the <hi>Church of God,</hi> knew not how to direct ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelves or others, in matters of faith or order, without inſtructions from abroad; yea we vvere then in a bevvildred condition, without officers and ſome of the ordinances, and profeſſed our ſelves to be a people that had loſt our way, and that vvere ſeekers of the way to <hi>Syon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 As for my purſuing it vvith <hi>much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> I knovv not vvhat he meanes, unleſſe it be that I refuſed to be ſatisfied vvith their <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations,</hi> vvhen they gave me no ſufficient ground for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 2. Secondly, vvhen it vvas moved in the <hi>Church</hi> to this effect, That it vvas very neceſſary to have reſpect in our admiſſion of <hi>Church members</hi> to union in Judgment, (at leaſt in all the ordinances of Chriſt) that peace and love in the <hi>Church</hi> might be preſerved; ſhe did eagerly contend againſt this motion, and occaſioned long and ſad diſputes betvveen the <hi>Church and her ſelfe,</hi> eſpecially concerning <hi>ſinging of Pſalmes,</hi> the practice of vvhich ſhe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170370:41"/>
abſolutely denied, and declared <hi>That praiſes and thankſgivings unto God in prayer were only that ſinging which the Scripture requireth.</hi> This alſo the generality of the then Church mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers did vvitneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> vvas not preſent at this meeting.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe vvho made this motion vvere ſome of them very vveak and erronious in their Judgment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When this motion vvas made, vve were without ſome of the <hi>ordinances,</hi> and ſo continued for ſome yeares after this, And they who made this motion were of a very <hi>indifferent Spirit,</hi> as to the procureing them, untill they had ſetled themſelves in publique offices. This was ſuch a burden unto mee, as that I was very much diſſatiſfied; when as they (who needed ſome to enforme their Iudgments) who made ſo litle Reckoning of the <hi>ordinances,</hi> ſhould yet be ſo forward after union in Iudgment: I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the worke we had to doe, was to free our ſelves from that <hi>Confuſion</hi> in which we were, by getting officers and ordinances.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As to Singing of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> It's true, I did at that time queſtion it, which doth adminiſter matter of daily humiliation unto me, to conſider and remember the darknes of my minde, that hath and continually doth, cauſe mee to wander from the way of the lord to the right hand and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170370:41"/>
to the left; But yet Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> hath litle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Charge me with it, for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He was the firſt that <hi>unſetled</hi> mee as to this <hi>practiſe,</hi> by Speaking againſt it himſelfe, &amp;</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some of his members have ſpoken more ſlightingly of this ordinance then ever I did, in affirming that one who was poſſeſſed of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell would ſinge <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> that they who ſunge <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> ſunge lyes &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The generality of the People that were for <hi>ſeperation</hi> every where Scrupled <hi>Singing,</hi> as to the matter, manner, place or time: So that it was a vaine thing at ſuch a time to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect vnion as to this ordinance, much more to preſſe it ſo eagerly, as to make it a neceſſary qualification of Church member ſhip, when as the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>Him that is weake in the faith receiue you, but not to doubtfull diſputations:</hi> whereupon I did oppoſe, not union, ſo much as the pride and irregularity of three members,</p>
               <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Owen,</hi> and <hi>John Whitehorne</hi> (then ſervant to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Mayne</hi>) who tooke upon them to deny <hi>Admiſsion</hi> unto two perſons who propoſed themſelves, becauſe they differed in judgment about the <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of this <hi>ordinance,</hi> and that before it was debated by the Church (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting at that time onely of eight or nine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) when as admitting or refuſing of perſons was then accounted a <hi>Church act,</hi> that which was to be debated by the whole. Theſe perſons did
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170370:42"/>
affectionately declare, that they were in the darke about the manner of <hi>ſinging,</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether it were a praiſing of God in a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall tune, or praiſing of him in prayer: one of them being asked, whether ſhee looked on <hi>ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Pſalmes</hi> as an ordinance of God, ſhee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that ſhe lookt on praiſing of God, as an ordinance of God, and as for <hi>ſinging,</hi> as now u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſhe could not ſay but it might be an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, however it was doubtfull to her: This perſon was afterwards received into the <hi>Church,</hi> and hath atteſted this under her owne hand; ſo that its evident, theſe words were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by others, and if I did afterwards ſpeake them, it was on the behalfe of thoſe perſons whoſe judgement I ſpake, more then mine own. And farther, the deſire I had to be informed concerning it, put mee upon objecting many things againſt it, eſpecially vvhen M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley</hi> vvas preſent: for this cauſe alſo vvas I very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt vvith them to procure an able Miniſter, as all the then <hi>Church</hi> can vvitneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 3. Thirdly, ſhe hath oppoſed ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perſons in their <hi>Admiſſion,</hi> vvho have beene knovvne to be of approved <hi>godlineſſe</hi> and <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity;</hi> and thoſe vvho have beene moſt lyable to <hi>Exception,</hi> ſhe hath moſt contended for, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the <hi>Church,</hi> having reſpited the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of a perſon concerning vvhoſe <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> they vvere not ſufficiently ſatisfied; ſhe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170370:42"/>
did openly declare againſt it, in theſe vvords, That it was an <hi>unrighteous ſentence:</hi> this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular vvas vvitneſſed by foure perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> As to the former part of the <hi>Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> my oppoſing perſons (reputed godly) in their admiſſions, I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. They themſelves have done the ſame, as appeares in my anſvver to the <hi>Accuſation</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately preceding this: They denyed admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to tvvo perſons, eſteemed godly, becauſe they ſcrupled <hi>Singing,</hi> and for their unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſpeake their Experiences in a publique meeting.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I never oppoſed any for their godlineſſe, and as for any who were eſteemed godly, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver oppoſed them alone, without other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, why am I therefore more <hi>Contentious</hi> then they?</p>
               <p n="3">3. They vvere not all godly vvhom I oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as is evident in <hi>Ganicle,</hi> vvho after his <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> (vvhich I vvithſtood) turned <hi>Quaker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the ſecond part of the <hi>Accuſation,</hi> my contending for thoſe vvho vvere moſt lyable to <hi>exception,</hi> I anſvver. The perſons I conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for are novv many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Church-members,</hi> and ſuch (I conceive) as Mr <hi>Stucley,</hi> and the reſt, do not novv looke upon as lyable to <hi>exception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>perſon</hi> concerning vvhom <hi>I</hi> uſed thoſe vvords, that it vvas an <hi>unrighteous ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> it vvas <hi>A. P.</hi> one generally accounted
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170370:43"/>
godly, yea Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe hath given this <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of her often, that ſhe vvould oppoſe <hi>Sin</hi> vvhere ever ſhe found it, that ſhee vvould not feare to <hi>Reprove</hi> it, vvhere ever ſhe came, ſhee being in <hi>fellowſhip</hi> vvith us from the firſt beginning, did at length propoſe her ſelfe to be admitted a <hi>Church-member,</hi> but this vvas denied her, becauſe of her unwillingneſſe to declare her <hi>Experiences</hi> in a publique meeting, this vvas the onely reaſon (that ever <hi>I</hi> heard) vvhy ſhe vvas then kept off.</p>
               <p>Aftervvards, vvhen the <hi>Admiſſion</hi> of <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> began to be in private, ſhe propoſed her ſelfe againe, but vvas refuſed the ſecond time, becauſe that ſome had a <hi>prejudice</hi> againſt her, for vvhich (as <hi>I</hi> conceived) they had little rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the things vvhereof ſhe was accuſed were triviall, neither were they ſufficiently proved, yea Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe cleared her, as to ſome one of the particulars: and although ſhe vvas in <hi>ſocietie</hi> with us for ſome yeares, yet ſhe was not permitted to ſpeake for her ſelfe: Her <hi>compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> alſo, a <hi>Church-member,</hi> who lived continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with her by reaſon of her many weakneſſes, was ready to anſvver for her, but it vvould not be permitted.</p>
               <p>After this meeting vvas diſmiſt, <hi>I</hi> deſired M. <hi>Stucley</hi> that I might not be preſent at ſuch debates, for I lookt on this as an <hi>unrighteous judgement,</hi> of vvhich he ſeemed then to take no
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170370:43"/>
great notice: if he vvere offended at that <hi>expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> vvhy did he not preſently examine vvhat ground I had for it? vvhy did hee not convince me of the <hi>Equity</hi> of their proceedings? vvhich untill it be done, I cannot but looke on it to this day as an <hi>unrighteous ſentence,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſentence</hi> as they have cauſe to be humbled for. It is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to thoſe, vvho vvere acquainted vvith her, how that ſhe vvas a perſon that had beene under great <hi>Terrours of minde,</hi> and <hi>affliction of ſpirit,</hi> even from her youth, that ſhe vvalked very ſadly continually, partly by reaſon of the vveakneſſe of her body, and partly by reaſon of thoſe <hi>temptations,</hi> vvith vvhich her vvhole life was acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied. ſo that it is not to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, if ſhe vvere troubled at her being twice refuſed <hi>admiſsion,</hi> by thoſe vvhom ſhe did ſo highly honour; and that ſhe vvas ſo exceedingly troubled at it, appeares by what ſhe ſaid to mee tvvo daies before her death, vvhich vvas vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fevv dayes after they had denyed to admit her, ſhe then told mee that their <hi>cruell dealing</hi> vvas the cauſe of her <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> and would be the cauſe of her <hi>death.</hi> And vvhen ſhee vvas told that <hi>death</hi> could not come till his <hi>commiſsion</hi> vvas ſealed by him vvho had the keyes of <hi>hell</hi> and <hi>death;</hi> ſhe anſvvered, ſhee knevv that very vvell, but yet they vvere the inſtruments which had effected it: ſhee deſired mee likewiſe to tell them of their <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> and to beware of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170370:44"/>
them; ſhe likewiſe grieved very much that Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> came not unto her when ſhe ſent for him in her <hi>ſickneſſe:</hi> however ſhe teſtified her love unto the <hi>Church</hi> and him, by leaving them both <hi>Legacies:</hi> the morning after ſhe dyed Mr <hi>R.</hi> (as I heard) came to the houſe, and did with teares in his eyes, tell her companion to this effect, that he and his wife had bleſſed God ſolemnly for that they had no hand in this <hi>cenſure.</hi> Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe honoured her ſo farre after ſhee was dead, as to preach her <hi>funerall Sermon:</hi> by all which it appeares how little reaſon hee hath to charge mee with being disſatisfied with their <hi>cenſuring</hi> her, and calling it an <hi>unrighteous ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> when as others beſides my ſelfe did not looke on it as <hi>righteous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 4. Shee oppoſed the <hi>Admiſſion</hi> of D. E. for her Ioyning with the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> in the ordinance of the <hi>lords Supper,</hi> &amp; inſiſted upon it with much Earneſtnes, ſhee then declareing that ſhee could not be ſatisfied otherwiſe, then by her acknowledging it to be her <hi>Sin</hi> in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>law of Charity:</hi> This was witneſſed by Seaven perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solution.</hi> This cannot prove me <hi>Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> any more then the generality of them, who have acknowledged that they did ſpeak againſt her; and ſome of them told me, that whereas I had one thing againſt her, they had twenty: yea Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe was ſo diſſatisfied with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170370:44"/>
her, as that he took advice with another mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter about her; but I remember the <hi>law of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to the dead, and therefore forbear to adde any more, but refer the Reader to my <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> where ſhe is brought in as a witneſſe againſt me for <hi>lying,</hi> as ſhe is here to prove me <hi>contentious.</hi> Surely if Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> did ever love her whiles ſhe lived, the beſt <hi>teſtimony</hi> he can give of it will be by letting her alone, to reſt quietly in her grave, and not urge me any more to publiſh that, which the <hi>law of Charity</hi> requires to be concealed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſtance</hi> 5. She cauſed a great deale of <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance</hi> amongſt us after the Officers were choſen, in preſſing with much earneſtneſſe that Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> might be choſen Paſtor: this was witneſſed by three perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> I know not what he meanes by <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance,</hi> nor who was <hi>diſturbed,</hi> neither have I any ground to believe that I cauſed the leaſt <hi>diſturbance</hi> to any, as to this <hi>particular.</hi> If I had cauſed ſuch a great deale of diſturbance amongſt them, it might have been witneſſed by more than three witneſſes. And as for Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> I wonder they ſhould alleadge him as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of my Contentiouſneſſe now he is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, who when he was preſent in the name of the Church pronounced me innocent, as to this very <hi>impeachment,</hi> after he was Officer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inſt.</hi> 6. She did a long time contend for <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170370:45"/>
ſpeaking in the Church;</hi> and being <hi>admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed</hi> for practiſing accordingly, ſhe did openly profeſſe that ſhe would not be preſent at <hi>Church meetings</hi> when matters were debated, unleſſe ſhe might have that <hi>liberty,</hi> and being denied, ſhe ever ſince contemptuouſly negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>Church meetings,</hi> and ſlighted the <hi>officers</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In pag. 20 of Mr. <hi>Mall's</hi> book, he laies down the charge in theſe words. <hi>She took liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſpeaking in the Church for ſome time, and being reproved by me for it, from time to time there was a viſible decay of affection to me</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solut.</hi> That it is falſe, as to the whole charge taken together, appeares, in that there are none (as in the former particulars) menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned who did witneſſe it, neither will he ever find any (unleſſe they be <hi>deſperately hardned</hi>) that dare affirme it, which I ſhall make <hi>evident</hi> in my Anſwers to the ſeverall particulars there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt particular (viz.) ſhe took the the liberty of ſpeaking, and ſhe did a long time contend for <hi>womens ſpeaking</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1 As for <hi>womens ſpeaking</hi> it was uſually practiſed amongſt us by the reſt of my <hi>Sex.</hi> And it is well known that the power was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended at firſt to be in the body of the people, in the <hi>multitude,</hi> ſo that every one had the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170370:45"/>
of <hi>aſſenting</hi> or <hi>diſſenting,</hi> of <hi>arguing</hi> and <hi>debating</hi> any matter propoſed, whether <hi>men</hi> or <hi>women.</hi> If <hi>women</hi> were denied the liberty of <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> how could they declare their <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences:</hi> yea <hi>A. P.</hi> was kept off for refuſing this.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is falſe that I took the <hi>liberty of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> it was not only given me, but the <hi>liberty</hi> of being <hi>ſilent</hi> was denied me, and that by Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe, who would ſend for me at the meetings, even then when there was never a woman of the <hi>Church</hi> but my ſelfe: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards many times he would ſingle me out in the meetings, and urge me very earneſtly to declare my <hi>Judgment</hi> in reference to what had been propoſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to my contending for <hi>womens ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> by my former Anſwers it appeares, that Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> hath little reaſon to charge me with it, unleſſe he expected that I ſhould be as fickle as himſelfe, in taking up, and laying down <hi>opinions</hi> and <hi>practiſes,</hi> as they ſuited with, or thwarted his <hi>humour</hi> and <hi>intereſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the ſecond particular, whereas he ſaith he <hi>admoniſhed</hi> and <hi>reproved</hi> me for it from time to time, I anſwer,</p>
               <p>That all the <hi>Admonition</hi> and <hi>Reproofe</hi> I had from him, was that mentioned in my <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> viz: that my ſpeaking was diſreliſhd by ſome, whereupon I reſolved <hi>Silence</hi> for the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170370:46"/>
future, although I had looked on the Contrary as my duty formerly; which reſolution I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinglie kept alwaies after the Officers were choſen, unleſſe it were when I was required to give in my thoughts concerning a perſon, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed or asked a queſtion; yea Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> witneſſeth for me in the charge it ſelfe, where he ſaith, it was a long time that I contended for <hi>womens ſpeaking,</hi> and in Mr <hi>Mall's</hi> book for ſome time &amp;c. By which it is evident that I did not continue in the practiſe thereof to the laſt: how can then my ſpeaking be brought as an Inſtance to prove me <hi>contentious</hi> (one ground of their <hi>Suſpenſion</hi>) neer three yeares after <hi>I</hi> had left of this practiſe.</p>
               <p>As for what he ſaith followed on his <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> and <hi>admoniſhing</hi> me, viz. 1 A decay of <hi>Affection</hi> to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> anſwer, if there were ſuch a viſible decay of <hi>affection,</hi> he miſtook the cauſe of it. It was not his <hi>reproving</hi> of me, no, the <hi>reproof</hi> was ſo mild and gentle, and at ſuch a diſtance, as that <hi>I</hi> had litle reaſon to be <hi>angry</hi> with him for it. But it was his <hi>ſelfe-ſeeking,</hi> and minding his <hi>own things</hi> more then the <hi>things of Chriſt</hi> &amp;c. againſt which <hi>I</hi> did declare my diſlike both before and after this <hi>reproof</hi> and <hi>admonition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to what he ſaies, <hi>that after their denying me the libertie of ſpeaking, I contemptuouſly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Church meetings, and ſlighted the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170370:46"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> anſwer that it is a <hi>groſſe lye,</hi> a lye ſo <hi>egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious,</hi> as that the whole <hi>church</hi> can vvitneſſe (if they pleaſe) againſt it.</p>
               <p>For I was after this conſtantly at <hi>church mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> the liberty of <hi>ſpeaking</hi> by a Brother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allowed me; yea I declared that I was very much diſſatisfied, becauſe the meetings (after the Officers were choſen) for conferring one with another, were not continued as formerly, I never abſented my ſelfe, but upon ſome ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary hindrance, which was not often.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>ſlighting of the Officers</hi>—</p>
               <p>I anſwer, that I gave them ſo much honour as was due unto them according to my power; if they had not ſo much as they deſired, let them conſider whether they did not deſire more then they deſerved. <hi>They that rule well, are worthy of double honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>Charge.</hi> The <hi>Cenſoriouſneſs</hi> of her <hi>Spirit</hi> was evide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in her <hi>uncharitable language</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the <hi>Preſbyterians,</hi> and us alſo: reporting one to be <hi>fallen from the faith,</hi> another to have <hi>nothing of God in her;</hi> charging Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> to have walked contrary to the <hi>Apoſtles counſell,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. And to have ſuch expreſſions in <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>prayer,</hi> as were but as <hi>chaffe</hi> to the <hi>wheat.</hi> And imputing the afflictions of ſome of the <hi>church</hi> to their unworthy receiving of the Lords body. Theſe were proved by many witneſſes, and her own letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170370:47"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> As to the firſt <hi>Article,</hi> vvhich con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> I anſvver, I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knovvledge &amp; confeſſe, that difference in <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> did likewiſe cauſe ſome breach in <hi>affection,</hi> that I vvas too much ſvvayed vvith a <hi>ſpirit of ſeparation,</hi> vvhich made mee prone to <hi>cenſure</hi> thoſe vvho differed from mee in <hi>judgment</hi> more then vvas fit, vvhich I have cauſe to bevvaile and lament. But yet I cannot but vvonder that Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> ſhould be ſo farre blinded vvith <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> as to cenſure mee for this, vvhen it is vvell knovvne that neither himſelfe, nor any of his <hi>Congregation,</hi> are in a <hi>capacity</hi> to fling ſo much as one ſtone at mee upon this account. It is now the fifth time hee hath mentioned the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in his threefold <hi>Accuſation;</hi> for what reaſon, though he himſelfe knowes beſt, yet others cannot be ignorant of, and as for the hope he puts in this, I believe it will prove but a <hi>Spiders web.</hi> I ſhall onely adde this, That if my <hi>Tongue</hi> were againſt the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> ſo would my hand likewiſe, had I harkened to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to my <hi>uncharitable language</hi> concerning themſelves, he doth inſtance in ſeverall particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, which I ſhall anſwer in that order he layes them downe, having deſired him in the generall to conſider thoſe reproachfull, bitter, unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>Raylings</hi> againſt Mris <hi>Allen</hi> and my ſelfe, wherewith both his <hi>Pamphlets</hi> are full, and ſee
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170370:47"/>
whether they doe not farre exceed all the hard ſpeeches I have given of them.</p>
               <p>As for the particulars they are <hi>(viz.)</hi> 1. My reporting one to be <hi>fallen from the faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> I do not remember that ever I uſed ſuch an <hi>expreſſion</hi> in <hi>reference</hi> to any of them, as <hi>(fallen from the faith.)</hi> There was (its true) one, concerning whom, when they were about to chooſe him to be an <hi>Officer,</hi> I ſaid, that I did feare he was not <hi>ſound in the faith,</hi> for which I had good ground, neither did I hereby intend to <hi>reproach</hi> that perſon, but to prevent the evill that might follow, in caſe one not ſound in the faith were choſen an Officer.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. That another had nothing of God in her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> I never heard the leaſt hint from them of any ſuch expreſſion, neither do I remember that I ever uſed it concerning any among them. If it be that perſon which I admoniſhed, that is meant by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley,</hi> as I have ſome ground to <hi>conjecture,</hi> for I cannot conceive who it ſhould be elſe. Then I ſay that it is a groſſe miſtake, if no worſe, to affirme that I reported, that ſhee had nothing of God in her.</p>
               <p>Shee was a perſon that pretended to a great deale of <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> whereupon I was willing to have ſome conference with her, to know if ſhee had any ground for ſuch an <hi>aſſurance.</hi> To this I was the more willing, becauſe a <hi>member</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> did ſomewhat queſtion it, who deſired
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170370:48"/>
me to try whether it were ſo or no, which <hi>I</hi> did: in my diſcourſe <hi>I</hi> told her, that they who had this <hi>aſſurance</hi> knew how they came by it, that where there is <hi>aſſurance,</hi> there is likewiſe <hi>adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> a cloſing with the <hi>promiſes,</hi> the workings whereof will be evident to that ſoul which hath attained it, that therefore ſhe ſhould do well to look to the <hi>ground</hi> of her <hi>confidence,</hi> and be ſure that ſhe had <hi>Scripture</hi> for it. What her anſwers were <hi>I</hi> ſhall not here mention; but it ſeemes ſhe did not like this my plaine and faithfull dealing with her, as appeares by her complaining of it to ſome, who hereupon have now accuſed mee for being ſo <hi>cenſorious</hi> as to affirme that ſhe had nothing of God in her, which is falſe; yea, <hi>I</hi> was ſo unwilling to diſhearten her, as that I told her, that <hi>grace</hi> was in the <hi>hidden man of the heart,</hi> and not <hi>diſcernable</hi> many times where it is, though <hi>aſſurance</hi> hath alvvayes its <hi>evidence.</hi> Had <hi>I</hi> knovvne that they had been offended vvith me for this, <hi>I</hi> ſhould have given them a full <hi>Account</hi> of vvhat paſſed betvveen us, whereby they vvould have knovvne the truth of vvhat was reported concerning her: this had beene farre better then to accuſe mee for it ſo many yeares after.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to that of Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> I muſt confeſſe that when Mr <hi>Stone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> refuſed to declare the End of that <hi>faſt</hi> mentioned in my <hi>Narrative,</hi> I did look upon
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170370:48"/>
it as walking in <hi>Craftineſſe,</hi> contrary to that of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</p>
               <p>And as to his <hi>Expreſsions</hi> in preaching &amp;c. <hi>I</hi> conceived Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> the fitteſt to admoniſh him of his weakneſſe; and therefore in a letter, I wrot unto him theſe following words. "I ſhall intreat you to ſpeak to Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> of thoſe Expreſſions he doth often uſe to expreſſe <hi>ſpirituall things</hi> by; the <hi>word</hi> (I conceive) is fitteſt to expreſſe <hi>ſpirituall myſteries and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:</hi> I am ſure that is the <hi>ſword of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>that is able to make the man of God perfect, throughly furniſhed to all good works. The more wiſe the preacher was, the more he ſought to teach the people wiſdome, and to find out acceptable words, words of wiſdome, that are as nailes and goads faſtned by the maſter of the Aſſembly:</hi> I muſt confeſſe I cannot cloſe with his Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which are uſuall and ordinary both in prayer and preaching, which is as the Chaffe to the wheate; and what is the chafte to the wheat? I ſhould ſpeak to him my ſelfe, but I fear he will not hear it from me.</p>
               <p>The ground on which <hi>I</hi> went, was that of the Apoſtle: <hi>ſay to Archippus, take heed to thy miniſtry that thou fulfill it.</hi> Would it have been an <hi>ingenuous</hi> returne of <hi>Archippus</hi> to cenſure, ſuſpend, or <hi>excommunicate</hi> a perſon for giving him ſuch an <hi>admonition?</hi> let Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> judge.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, concerning my imputing the <hi>afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170370:49"/>
of ſome of the <hi>church</hi> to their unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> For anſwer hereunto, <hi>I</hi> ſhall here ſet down what I wrote in the ſame letter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, viz.</p>
               <p>"It is and hath been a great trouble to me, that there is no meanes of inſtructing by <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing,</hi> which is like, in my apprehenſion, to put a ſtop in the way of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> And <hi>I</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ordinance of the <hi>Lords ſupper</hi> cannot be kept pure, without <hi>inſtructing</hi> thoſe that are of the Church, younger ones eſpecially, in the myſtery of diſcerning the <hi>Lords body:</hi> for this many are weake and ſick, the Apoſtle laies it down as a Cauſe of that <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> and <hi>death</hi> that was amongſt them. For my part it is my <hi>feare</hi> that the Lord hath a <hi>controverſie</hi> with us for not diſcerning the Lords body, and not judging our ſelves. Surely the Lords hand that is upon us, and thoſe afflictions that have been upon me, hath put me upon ſerious enquiry after the Lord in his word; and <hi>I</hi> am afraid we do not walk up to our own <hi>principles,</hi> and keep the <hi>ordinances</hi> pure.</p>
               <p>Behold Mr. <hi>Stucley's</hi> diſcretion and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity in cenſuring me for cenſuring my ſelfe, which <hi>I</hi> did in that letter as well as others. <hi>I</hi> did impute the <hi>afflictions</hi> on my ſelfe and them, either to the omitting of the <hi>administration</hi> of the <hi>Lords ſupper</hi> for a long time, without giving
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170370:49"/>
any reaſon; or to our not diſcerning the <hi>Lords body,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> was perſwaded that many amongſt us by reaſon of their ignorance could not do, <hi>I</hi> did verily think that the Lord was angry with us for this. <hi>I</hi> was ſo ſenſible of Gods <hi>afflicting hand,</hi> as that <hi>I</hi> could not but diſcover my fear unto Mr. <hi>Stucley,</hi> that he might ſet upon reforming what was amiſſe, for <hi>I</hi> thought <hi>I</hi> had herein to do with <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and not with <hi>Scorners:</hi> it was the leaſt of my thoughts, that ever <hi>I</hi> ſhould be cenſured for it.</p>
               <p>Having finiſhed his threefold charge, he proceeds to adde ſomewhat concerning my <hi>contumacious refuſall of admonition</hi> in pag. 45. of his Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Toby Allen,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>I might tell thee I have ſeverall times endeavoured to convince her of her ſin, yet I doe not remember that ever ſhe acknowledged her ſelfe guilty, and that ſeverall perſons that were ſent to her (or that went voluntarily) about the worke of admonition, came away from her with a burdned ſpirit. But I ſhall referre thee to</hi> 20 &amp; 21 <hi>pag: of my Sermon in the true Account</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here he tells the world that I refuſed <hi>admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,</hi> firſt from <hi>himſelfe,</hi> ſecondly from <hi>others,</hi> and then refers the Reader for farther Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the <hi>true Account,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1 As to his <hi>admonition</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I might tell thee I have ſeverall times &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170370:50"/>
                  <hi>Reſol,</hi> You cannot tell this without <hi>telling a lye,</hi> for I was never admoniſhed by you for any ſin that I continued in after admonition, either before my leaveing you or ſince.</p>
               <p>Not before. This you acknowledged to me when I asked, whether you had ever admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed me, you told me you had not: this you confeſſed to Mr. <hi>Ford</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bartlett.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not ſince. For I could never ſpeak with you, after you had accuſed me of <hi>lying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Its true you <hi>admoniſhed</hi> me for hearing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miniſter; but that this is a ſin, you dare not (it ſeems) affirme or maintaine: for it is not ſo much as named among thoſe <hi>Crimes</hi> laid to my charge either in the <hi>true account,</hi> or in your Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Toby Allen.</hi> And therefore what reaſon is there that I ſhould acknowledge my ſelfe guilty?</p>
               <p n="2">2 As to the Second (viz.) that ſeverall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that were ſent unto her &amp;c. came away with <hi>burdened Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> The errand they came about was not to <hi>admoniſh</hi> me for lying &amp;c. But partly to take me off from hearing other <hi>miniſters,</hi> and ſince I left them to perſwade me back again: it was my not conſenting unto them in this, that made them go away with a <hi>burthen'd ſpirit,</hi> and not becauſe of my <hi>proud and loftie Carriage</hi> (as he ſaith pag. 20 <hi>True Acc:</hi>) for I alwaies treated with them <hi>Civilly,</hi> returning
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170370:50"/>
them thanks ſeverall times for their (pretended love) to me; I never baulkt diſcourſe with them. And alwaies at their departing, ſaid, let me be convinced from the word what my duty is, and I ſhall ſubmit.</p>
               <p>I deſired the <hi>Elder</hi> before the faſt in order to their <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and ſince that <hi>faſt</hi> others alſo, that they would bring the buſineſſe to a new Triall before the miniſters, whom they themſelves had acquainted with it former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with whom I was then in <hi>Communion:</hi> had the Inceſtuous perſon done ſo, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded he would never have been delivered to Satan.</p>
               <p>The letter likewiſe ſent Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> by Mris. <hi>Allen</hi> and my ſelfe makes it evident, that neither of us <hi>contemptuouſly</hi> refuſed <hi>admonition</hi> according to the rule of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 As for his referring the reader to pag. 20. 21. of the <hi>true Account,</hi> as if there were other <hi>Crimes</hi> mentioned there, for brevities ſake he omitted here, I ſay.</p>
               <p>That in pag. 20 of the <hi>True</hi> (which yet ſome think to be a very <hi>defective) Account,</hi> there is only one <hi>Crime</hi> mentioned, which he hath not accuſed me of here in this other Book, and that is my <hi>unfaithfulneſſe</hi> in not reproving privately.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charge.</hi> I am confident (ſaith he) that there is ſcarce one <hi>Brother</hi> or <hi>Siſter</hi> that can bear witneſſe of her faithfulneſſe in <hi>Reproving
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170370:51"/>
privately,</hi> though ſhe ſo much Blazon'd abroad ſuppoſed or reall infirmities, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> 1, I am Confident that ſome can (if they will not <hi>hold the truth in unrighteouſneſſe</hi>) bear witneſſe of my <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> in reproving them privately, I reproved Mr. <hi>Raddon</hi> and his wife, Mr <hi>Eveleighs maide,</hi> yea Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> himſelfe, both privately, and publickly when his offence was publick, according to that of the Apoſt. 1 Tim. 5.20. And if none of theſe will witneſſe, yet Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe can, if he call himſelfe to mind, he can bear me witneſſe, that I reproved him for his <hi>indifferency of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> in the worke of God, for his preaching <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Sermons,</hi> for his <hi>Serpentine ſubtilty</hi> in his Entrance on his Office, and in reference to his Carriage in Mr. <hi>Madder's</hi> buſineſſe, yea he hath witneſſed that I reproved him for the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ſentence</hi> in reference to A. P.</p>
               <p n="2">2 As for Blazoning abroad their ſuppoſed or reall infirmities, I know not what he meanes, or of what thing he ſpeaks it, whether whiles I was with them, or ſince I left them.</p>
               <p>If he mean thereby that when I was among them, <hi>I</hi> did diſcover the nakedneſſe of a <hi>Brother</hi> or <hi>Siſter</hi> to others who were not in <hi>Communion</hi> with us, <hi>I</hi> ſay it is falſe, and dare him to inſtance ſo much as in one particular.</p>
               <p>If by <hi>abroad,</hi> he meane others of the <hi>Society, I</hi> acknowledge it. But then it was to ſuch as
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170370:51"/>
by reaſon of their intimacy and familiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the <hi>offendors</hi> might in all probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty prevaile, more vvith them then I could. And for this very reaſon did I ſeveral times ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe my ſelfe to Mr. <hi>Stucley,</hi> which he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth a litle before this charge, though, through <hi>Envy,</hi> he call it an <hi>Impeachment</hi> and accuſe me for it, though I had the houſe of <hi>Cloe</hi> for my Example.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, If <hi>(By abroad)</hi> he meane that I have divulged their miſcarriages to others ſince I left them, To this I anſwer.</p>
               <p>That even ſince my leaveing them, It was my deſire to continue a good opinion of many among them: So unwilling was I to make knowen that which might blemiſh any of them, As that I ſuffered in mine owne name, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing their miſcarriages, untill ſuch time as it was noiſed abroad, that I had not left them, but that they had caſt me out as a <hi>lyer,</hi> a <hi>contentious</hi> and a <hi>troubleſome perſon,</hi> whom they could no longer Suffer, nor have <hi>communion</hi> with: Then indeed I did begin to pull off their <hi>masking robes</hi> and <hi>vizards,</hi> as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley</hi> expreſſeth it in the <hi>true Account,</hi> that ſo it might appeare to the world, how unlikely it was, that ſuch (as many of them were) ſhould caſt off any upon the <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> of <hi>lying.</hi> Againe,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charge.</hi> In <hi>pag.</hi> 21. He brings in a <hi>paſſionate expreſſion</hi> of mine in theſe words, And being
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170370:52"/>
farther preſſed to heare the Church, ſhe refuſed, and (if my memory faile not) ſhe ſaid, <hi>She would be drawn aſunder by wild horſes rather then come among us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> I confeſſe the <hi>expreſſion,</hi> whether there were not cauſe for it, let others <hi>judge,</hi> they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving dealt ſo baſely with mee as to accuſe me of <hi>lying,</hi> when I went unto them a little before to give them a reaſon why I left them. <hi>A burnd child</hi> (we ſay) <hi>dreads the fire:</hi> I had been burnd once by adventuring ſingly among them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I durſt not do it againe the <hi>ſecond</hi> time. So that Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> needed not here to inſert this <hi>parentheſis</hi> (if my memory faile me not) it would have done better in all the other <hi>Articles</hi> of his <hi>accuſation,</hi> in which, if his memory did not faile him, he will never be able to free himſelfe from that, for which he pretends he hath <hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated</hi> mee.</p>
               <p>But that I did not refuſe to heare the <hi>Church,</hi> the ſeverall anſwers I gave to the meſſengers ſent me can witneſſe. Beſides, when M. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> came to acquaint mee with the Faſt, in order to <hi>Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication. I</hi> deſired that the buſineſſe my might be referred to Mr <hi>Forde,</hi> and Mr <hi>Bartlet,</hi> who had formerly heard it: and after the Faſt <hi>I</hi> told two other of their members, that they ſhould bring it to a new tryall before the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Exeter</hi> with whom I was in <hi>Communion,</hi> promiſing to ſtand to their <hi>determination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170370:52"/>The letter likewiſe Mris <hi>Allen</hi> and my ſelfe ſent the <hi>Church,</hi> doth witneſſe ſufficiently, that neither of us refuſed to heare the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Unto this Charge he addes that of <hi>ſeparation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charge.</hi> And though ſhee had lifted up her right hand to heaven to walk in fellowſhip with us, yet hath ſhe <hi>ſeparated</hi> from us, and to this day ſought not <hi>reconciliation,</hi> neither hath ſhee expreſſed <hi>Repentance</hi> for her <hi>Sinne,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> This is likewiſe confeſt and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that <hi>I Seperated</hi> from them, The grounds of my <hi>Separation</hi> are layed downe in my <hi>narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> To which <hi>I</hi> ſhall farther adde.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there was a clauſe in our firſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> binding every one of us not to reſt in the light then received, but to Studie to knowe the minde of God, and live up to it, and ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly haveing Studied the minde of God, concerning our <hi>ſeparation</hi> from other Churches of Chriſt, <hi>I</hi> founde it to be <hi>Sinfull,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore durſt no longer to continue therein.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If <hi>I</hi> engaged ſo to walke in <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with you as to deny it to others of <hi>Gods people,</hi> of which there are many (I hope) in this <hi>Citty,</hi> I am Sorry for it, and to ſhew my <hi>Repentance</hi> I have reformed, by leaveing your <hi>Society.</hi> in which I could not continue without the guilt of <hi>Sin,</hi> If a man ſhould promiſe, yea Sweare to that, which is <hi>Sin</hi> he had better to break then to keepe his oath.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170370:53"/>yea we were likewiſe engaged to hold <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with other <hi>Churches of Chriſt;</hi> But this is now denyed, unleſſe it be with thoſe that are <hi>Congregationall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for what he addes concerning my not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing <hi>repentance</hi> for my ſin: &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol. I</hi> ſhall anſwer with <hi>Job: c.</hi> 27. <hi>God forbid that I ſhould juſtify you</hi> (by confeſſing that which I am not guilty of) <hi>till I die, I will not remove my integrity from me. My righteouſneſſe</hi> (as to your impeachment) <hi>I hold faſt, and will not let it goe: my heart ſhall not reproach me</hi> (for baſely ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to any thing againſt my conſcience) <hi>ſo long as I live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In pag. 23. He ſpeaks of my undervaluing, <hi>Excommunication</hi> &amp; ſlighting it, in theſe words <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other (meaning me) as little valued this <hi>Inſtitution of Chriſt</hi> for (as I am informed) ſhe ſaid, <hi>Excommunication was but as the breaking of a horſe over the hedge, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> I have been heretofore, and am at preſent ſo far from ſlighting <hi>excommunication</hi> rightly adminiſtred, as that it makes me trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to behold my ſelfe accuſed thereof, as if <hi>I</hi> ſlighted the <hi>ordinance</hi> it ſelfe: <hi>I</hi> look on it as an ordinance of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as that <hi>Sword</hi> which he hath given his <hi>Church</hi> for the cutting off <hi>contagious members,</hi> as that, which he hath appointed and ordained to as high an end (for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170370:53"/>
ought <hi>I</hi> know) as any other ordinance, <hi>(viz) the deſtruction of the fleſh, that the ſpirit may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the <hi>ſlighting expreſsion</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this ordinance, with which he chargeth me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ſay it is a <hi>notorious ſlander,</hi> as he hath laid it down, the truth is, that to ſome, who ſpake about <hi>excommunication I</hi> told them how it had been formerly abuſed in this nation by many who (as it was reported) would <hi>excommunicate</hi> for ſuch a <hi>Treſpaſſe,</hi> as a horſe to break over a hedge; and farther added, that I valued an unjuſt <hi>excommunication</hi> no more then <hi>I</hi> did that: and becauſe <hi>I</hi> look on M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucleys</hi> late <hi>excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> as ſuch, therefore do <hi>I</hi> ſet light by it: as <hi>Luther</hi> did by the <hi>Popes bull,</hi> for which he was never charged by any <hi>Proteſtant:</hi> in doing of which I am no more to be condemned for ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this ordinance in generall then he. It will be found upon triall that Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> hath a farre lower eſteeme of this <hi>ordinance,</hi> then my ſelfe, otherwiſe he would never have ſo abuſed it as he hath, for the promoting his own <hi>intereſt</hi> and <hi>carnall deſignes,</hi> which is the ready way to make it contemptible, in the Judgment and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of thoſe who are not well acquainted with it.</p>
               <p>Thus I have done with the <hi>true account,</hi> and now returne to what he ſaith farther concerning me in his anſwer to Mr <hi>Toby Allen:</hi> pag. 45.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170370:54"/>
                  <hi>Her Crimes and contumacy being very great: the Church thought themſelves obliged to ſuſpend her from Communion before ever ſhe joyned in the Sacrament with any other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> That this <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> was for no other <hi>crimes or contumacy,</hi> then my leaving them, and my refuſeing to returne unto them: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was not thought ſufficient to debarre me from <hi>communion</hi> with others of Gods people in this City, by thoſe who heard the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and throughly examined the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Char.</hi> In the next place he chargeth Mr <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> with a lye, for affirming. That the <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> between the <hi>Church</hi> and me began, becauſe I had a mind to heare ſome other <hi>miniſters</hi> which (he ſaith) is abominably falſe, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that this was no particular for which <hi>I</hi> was ever admoniſhed by the <hi>Church</hi> in pag. 45.46. And again, he ſaith, That the <hi>Quarrell</hi> began in my <hi>contentious Spirit</hi> and ſowing Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and was increaſed by <hi>lying.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſ.</hi> 1 That <hi>I</hi> was admoniſhed, for hearing other miniſters, by the Church it is manifeſt by what is allready ſet down.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That the <hi>quarrell</hi> did not begin in my <hi>contentious Spirit,</hi> and ſowing diviſions; nor was encreaſed by <hi>lying:</hi> it is alſo apparent, as for <hi>lying,</hi> I was never charged with it till I left them: and as for <hi>contention,</hi> &amp;c. I never medled with
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170370:54"/>
                  <hi>Church affaires</hi> after the officers were choſen; unleſſe it were once in reference to a perſon propoſed, when <hi>Ganicle</hi> interrupted me.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Qurarell</hi> Brake out at a <hi>Tueſdayes meeting,</hi> Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> was abſent from that meeting and ſo knowes nothing of it but by the report of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, it ſo much concerning mee, I have reaſon to know it better then others: The account whereof according to my beſt Remembrance is this.</p>
               <p>On the day before, being munday after dyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Mr. <hi>Stonham</hi> and his wife came to viſit me, Before <hi>I</hi> could come to them, my husband, in diſcourſing with them ſayed, that <hi>I</hi> had heard Mr. <hi>Ford</hi> the day before, when <hi>I</hi> came into the Roome, Mr <hi>Stonham</hi> looked on me with an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry countenance</hi> and would ſcarce Speak, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I asked his wife what did aile him, who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvered that he vvas not vvell pleaſed vvith me for my goeing avvay to heare, ſhe told me like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe that he did not like Mr <hi>Eveleighs</hi> maide, and farther added, that ſhe heard that I had ſomewhat againſt her, ſhe is (ſaid I) a ſtranger unto me, and therefore it is my deſire that ſhe may be kept off one week longer untill I have informed my ſelfe concerning her, Then (ſaid ſhe) do you be preſent at the meeting to ſpeak to have her kept off, this ſhe deſired with much earneſtneſſe.</p>
               <p>On the <hi>Tueſdaie</hi> following after dinner Mr
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170370:55"/>
                  <hi>Spraigue</hi> the younger came to me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mr <hi>Stone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> (as he ſaid) who had been with him the day before, and deſired him to take me off from hearing Mr <hi>Ford.</hi> To this end (among other things) he told me, <hi>that thoſe ſheep, which had been uſed to meane feeding, were not fit for fat paſture, it was the way to bring them to the ſcab:</hi> he likewiſe ſpake ſomething about Mr <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leighs</hi> maid, and earneſtly deſired me to be at the meeting. I told him that I then lay under ſome <hi>trouble of ſpirit,</hi> and ſo could not be fit for ſuch an <hi>Imployment,</hi> however upon his earneſt intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I fitted my ſelfe to goe.</p>
               <p>When I was come, they began (contrarie to their uſuall practice) to talke of the maid, before ever the Lord had been ſought unto in <hi>prayer:</hi> Mr <hi>Owen,</hi> ſitting at the table neer me, I willed him to acquaint them, that it was my deſire ſhe might be kept off a week longer (as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) untill I had informed my ſelfe concerning her.</p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Eveleigh,</hi> preſently replyed, that he would give <hi>Teſtimony</hi> for her: I told him that a <hi>maſter</hi> or <hi>ſuperior</hi> was not ſo fit to give <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> for a <hi>ſervant</hi> or <hi>inferior,</hi> and withall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced in <hi>Gehazi,</hi> who carried himſelfe fairly in his maſters preſence.</p>
               <p>After this one <hi>Ambroſe</hi> a ſhoomaker was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, who (it ſeemes) wrought with <hi>Ganicle,</hi> concerning whom Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> asked me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170370:55"/>
I had any thing againſt him? I anſwered that I had nothing, and alſo that though he were a ſtranger unto me, yet I had heard a good <hi>report</hi> of him: upon which <hi>Ganicle</hi> ſaid that I would take his <hi>Teſtimony</hi> for his man, and not Mr <hi>Eveleighs</hi> for his maid, yea (ſaid Mr <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi>) that is the very thing, becauſe it is my <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> therefore ſhe will not take it, adding farther that it was <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> and that I was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive or <hi>contentious,</hi> and had hindred their proceedings for many yeares, inſomuch as he could not partake with me in the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> untill he was <hi>ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I replyed, that this would not be borne, and that if my <hi>carriage</hi> had bin ſo offenſive, I ſhould have heard of it, in ſome other place and in ſome other manner: and then I preſently appealed to all the <hi>Congregation</hi> deſiring them to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto me, as they would <hi>Anſwer</hi> it another day, by declaring wherein my <hi>carriage</hi> had been <hi>offenſive,</hi> and what evils they had ſeen in me: And when I perceived they were unwilling to meddle in it, <hi>I</hi> told them plainly, that <hi>I</hi> would come no more among them, unleſs they would ſatisfie me herein.</p>
               <p>At length Mr <hi>Stoneham</hi> began his <hi>prayer</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner: <hi>Lord, we have waited for a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and now thou haſt given us in a prayer, it may be, the returne of many prayers,</hi> and then bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>that the ſerpent was gotten into the garden:</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170370:56"/>
After the prayer, <hi>Mr. Eveleigh</hi> and my ſelfe were to withdraw; but Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> (before he went out) told them, he left it to the <hi>Church</hi> to determine, whether I were not <hi>contentious.</hi> Two things (ſaid he) I have againſt her, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> and her going away to hear Mr <hi>Ford,</hi> which the <hi>Church</hi> neither can, nor will bear. And he farther charged <hi>John Whitehorne</hi> (the chiefeſt then in this buſineſſe) that he ſhould inſiſt upon <hi>Contention,</hi> and if he wanted an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> that he ſhould name <hi>Agnes Pullen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we were withdrawne, the generality of them ſaid, they did believe I was a good woman &amp;c. But then they were asked againe, whether through a mixture of <hi>Corruption</hi> it might not tend to <hi>Contention?</hi> to which this reply was made, That they did not know but it might. Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> told me, that they would not for a world charge me with <hi>contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but did fear leſt through a mixture of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> it might tend thereunto.</p>
               <p>Many of them were offended with the <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> dealing ſo diſorderly with me, but knew not how to help it, and deſired me to take no notice of it.</p>
               <p>By all which it appeares</p>
               <p n="1">1 That they were very much diſpleaſed with me for hearing others beſides our own Officers, though they were unwilling to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell with me openly about it. Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170370:56"/>
(tis true) accuſed me thereof at this meeting, but (as I am informed) ſome of them did very much diſlike his mentioning of that particular; and refuſed to medle with it, becauſe they thought it fitter to be concealed, then that it ſhould be publickly taken notice of.</p>
               <p n="2">2 That it is very probable they had a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution (ſome of them) to <hi>quarrell</hi> with me about Mr. <hi>Eveleigh's</hi> maid, in caſe I could not be prevailed with to leave off hearing of other miniſters, why elſe ſhould they be ſo earneſt with me (after I had given a <hi>ſufficient Excuſe</hi> for my abſence) to be preſent at the meeting? why elſe ſhould Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> uſe ſuch <hi>expreſſions</hi> in his prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">3 That although Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> at this time (when the <hi>Quarrell</hi> brake out) accuſed me of <hi>Contention;</hi> yet that the <hi>Quarrell</hi> did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in my <hi>contentious ſpirit,</hi> and ſowing diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is apparent. 1 Becauſe I did no more then Mr. <hi>Stoneham</hi> approved of, and Mris. <hi>Stoneham</hi> deſired me to do; ſo that I could be no more <hi>contentious</hi> in oppoſing Mr. <hi>Eveleighs</hi> mayd, then they. 2. This buſineſſe was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in three daies; they had nothing after this againſt me, but my hearing other miniſters, as Mr. <hi>Eveleigh</hi> himſelfe told me.</p>
               <p n="4">4 And therefore notwithſtanding the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell brake out at the time, when I oppoſed Mr. <hi>Eveleigh's</hi> maid, yet it is very apparent that it
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170370:57"/>
began, was continued, carried on, and increaſed even to a breach, only for my hearing of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther miniſter: for as to the charge of <hi>lying</hi> I never heard of it till my coming off, as I have already declared.</p>
               <p>In the next place he <hi>takes ſhame to himſelfe,</hi> that he did not ſooner excite the <hi>church</hi> to their duty, as to the laſt <hi>Remedy</hi> for the healing of this woman, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol. I</hi> believe in the end he will ſee more cauſe to <hi>take ſhame to unto himſelfe,</hi> in that he hath ſo raſhly excited them to this <hi>cenſure,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ever diſcharged the duty of <hi>admonition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let him conſider whether he hath not run before the Lord ſent him, let him produce his warrant to <hi>Excommunicate,</hi> before ever he proved the <hi>Crime,</hi> or admoniſhed me of the Evills, for which he ſaies <hi>I</hi> am <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He addes, that there are ſome full of evill ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes about this matter, as if the Church would never have proceeded againſt her, but upon a deſigne to hinder others from deſerting us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> It is no ſurmiſe, for</p>
               <p n="1">1 One of their own Officers (Mr. <hi>Slade</hi> by name) talking with an <hi>Alderman</hi> of this City about this <hi>Excommunication,</hi> told him that if they had proceeded againſt me ſooner, Mris. <hi>Allen</hi> would not have left them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170370:57"/>2 Mr. <hi>Stucley</hi> doth not in plain termes deny it. And though that which follows concerning the <hi>unquietneſse of his ſpirit</hi> about my not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting</hi> may imply a deniall, yet</p>
               <p n="3">3 It is that which he hath in a manner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged in pag. 10. of the <hi>True Account,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>If we had diſcharged our duty ſooner on the lyar, we might have prevented the others fall, her diſobedience and perverſeneſse of ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for that he profeſſeth, he had no quiet in his Spirit, that a Perſon ſhould lie ſo long ſuſpended, and give no <hi>Evidence</hi> of <hi>Repentance,</hi> but the Contrarie &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol:</hi> The <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> vvas tvvo moneths after I had left them; the meſſenger that vvas ſent to give me notice thereof ſayd it vvas in order to my <hi>Returne,</hi> a <hi>Returne</hi> to them, this is the <hi>Repentance</hi> they expected, and I reſolved againſt, unleſſe (as <hi>I</hi> told the <hi>Elder</hi>) I might have <hi>communion</hi> with them, and not to <hi>ſeparate</hi> from others that vvere godly.</p>
               <p>But vvhat quiet can Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> have novv, that he hath paſſed a <hi>Sentence of Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> vvithout <hi>admonition,</hi> ſeeing I ſo earneſtly deſired it? vwhat comfort can he have in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this <hi>Cenſure</hi> three yeares wanting a few daies after <hi>I</hi> had left them? when as in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability by reaſon of <hi>forgetfulneſſe,</hi> there could not be a <hi>charging of ſin,</hi> ſo as to convince and work a kindly <hi>Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If his <hi>conſcience</hi> had troubled him, becauſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170370:58"/>
of my lying in <hi>Sin,</hi> without evidencing <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> then his <hi>conſcience</hi> is either <hi>blind</hi> or <hi>baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled;</hi> elſe why had not his <hi>conſcience</hi> checkt him, when he diſcovered no <hi>zeale</hi> againſt <hi>lying,</hi> when he was ſo often preſt unto it by me? why had not his <hi>conſcience</hi> troubled him, when there was a <hi>lye</hi> affirmed with ſo much <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> by <hi>John Whitehorne,</hi> when he offered to depoſe it upon Oath, and yet there was clear <hi>Teſtimony</hi> brought by ſome of their members to prove it to be a <hi>lye?</hi> this perſon is under his <hi>charge,</hi> yet here his <hi>conſcience</hi> hath not diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.</p>
               <p>And for what he addes, <hi>That to quiet his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he tooke advice with ſeverall Miniſters, and ſo concluded the matter by them and his own Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> 1. Why did he go ſo farre away? had he deſired to have the truth brought to light, then why ſhould he refuſe to adviſe with thoſe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> that he himſelfe acquainted with the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe; and when <hi>I</hi> ſo often deſired them to bring it to a new tryall before them, with a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> to <hi>ſubmit</hi> unto their <hi>determinations,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expecting any favour from them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How could thoſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> (whoever they be) perſwade him to ſuch a <hi>cenſure,</hi> without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing him to bring the buſineſſe to a <hi>Triall,</hi> without hearing both parties ſpeake? will not <hi>Feſtus</hi> riſe up in judgement againſt them? Did theſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> in their <hi>advice</hi> duly weigh the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170370:58"/>
weight of this <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and the pretiouſneſſe of <hi>ſoules</hi> for which <hi>Chriſt</hi> did <hi>Sweat, Bleed</hi> and <hi>died,</hi> for which hee ever lives to make <hi>interceſſion?</hi> Durſt they upon the Report of one partie without Examination, give ſuch advice in a corner? the Lord lay not this ſin to their charge: 'Tis not the firſt time that <hi>Satan</hi> hath made uſe of ſuch <hi>inſtruments,</hi> Chriſt ſaw him in a <hi>Peter</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I</hi> confeſſe it would have been more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily borne, if they had been ſuch as have not knowne the Father, nor the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that had given this wicked advice; but that it ſhould come from them, who have (or at leaſt pretend to) more <hi>acquaintance with Chriſt</hi> then others, this is as the <hi>Vineger</hi> and the <hi>Gall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charg. p.</hi> 47. In the laſt place hee gives the world a <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>lying defamations,</hi> ſpoken by mee ſince my <hi>Suſpenſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſol.</hi> As for thoſe <hi>lying defamations,</hi> I anſwer briefly: That many of thoſe Reports are no <hi>lying Defamations,</hi> but manifeſt truths, as I have made it already to appeare in my <hi>Narrative</hi> and <hi>Vindication;</hi> and make no queſtion but ſhall be able to do the like of the reſt, if called unto it, even as many of them as he ſhall prove to proceed from mee, farre better then M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley</hi> will be able to make good (in a regular and orderly proceeding) thoſe <hi>ſlanderous reports</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning mee, with which he hath filled the world, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding he <hi>boaſts</hi> ſo much of <hi>witneſſes,</hi> at the end almoſt of every <hi>Charge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And novv <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe the <hi>Reader</hi> is ſufficiently tired vvith peruſing an unpleaſing and broken <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170370:59"/>
ſhall therefore now haſten to an End.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Goſpell</hi> be the great <hi>Salvation</hi> that is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, and the <hi>Revelation</hi> of it compleated, and it be once delivered to the <hi>Saints,</hi> and no other <hi>Revelation</hi> to be expected till <hi>Chriſt</hi> come, and this <hi>Salvation</hi> being ſo glorious, as that the <hi>Angels</hi> deſire to look into it, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a <hi>Curſe</hi> by Chriſt pronounced on ſuch as ſhall adde to it, or take from it, then let it ſerve as an <hi>Apology</hi> for me in my learning of them. This was that which I did deſire and aime at, that I might be inſtructed in the <hi>myſtery</hi> of this <hi>great Salvation, God manifeſt in the fleſh</hi> &amp;c. Tis that was in my eye, and that I ſtill follow after (although I have not yet attained) <hi>to comprehend with all Saints what is the bredth, and length, and depth, and heighth, and to know the love of Chriſt, which paſſeth knowledge;</hi> yet through grace this was, and is that one thing, that I may <hi>know Chriſt and him crucified,</hi> and that I may with the Apoſtle <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14. <hi>know him, and the power of his Reſurrection, and the fellowſhip of his Sufferings, ſo as to be made conformable to his death, that I may know this great myſtery which hath been hid from other ages, but is now revealed unto us by the holy Apoſtles and Prophets by the Spirit, Eph.</hi> 3.1. Know him ſo, as to <hi>bear about in my body the dying of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> that the life of Jeſus may be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in this mortall fleſh, that the <hi>old man may be Crucified with him, that the body of Sin might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, that I might not ſerve ſin;</hi> This was that which to the glory of <hi>free grace</hi> I can ſay in ſome meaſure
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170370:59"/>
(if my heart do not deceive me) was my deſire in Joyning with them, and in my withdrawing from them, I finding not a <hi>Sufficiency</hi> in their <hi>Miniſtry</hi> for <hi>edification</hi> and <hi>building up;</hi> and being diſapointed of my <hi>expectation</hi> in the <hi>miniſtry,</hi> and continuing my practice of hearing Mr <hi>Ford,</hi> ſometimes once a Lords day meerly out of neceſſity, and obſerving what they did after they were in office and ſetled themſelves, in ſtead of diſcovering their love and faithfulneſſe to the peoples ſoules in their diligent <hi>circumſpection</hi> and <hi>watchfulneſſe</hi> over them, and diſcovering to them the <hi>hidden myſteries of the Goſpell,</hi> they were very remiſſe, the worke they were imployed in was to <hi>exalt</hi> themſelves, and bring the people into <hi>Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> unto them, <hi>ſilenceing</hi> ſome, and <hi>cenſuring</hi> others without allowing them any liberty to clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſuch as they ſuppoſed ſtood in their way, and when this was effected, then they proceeded farther to take them off from hearing any other <hi>miniſter,</hi> making that practice of hearing another <hi>miniſter,</hi> when themſelves preached, to be a going out of the <hi>Boſome of Chriſt</hi> into the <hi>Boſome of Strangers;</hi> and ſuch perſons were <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Rebells</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt, and ſhould be ſo dealt withall; and what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit was received by another <hi>miniſter</hi> to be a delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion and a <hi>Temptation,</hi> and a <hi>Judgment of God</hi> upon the <hi>ſoule.</hi> And ingaging the people at their admiſſion, to believe it as an <hi>Article of their faith,</hi> that a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bleſſing was to be expected on their <hi>miniſtry,</hi> then on any others, as if they preached another Jeſus, or another Spirit, or another Goſpell: when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170370:60"/>
ſayeth, <hi>he that planteth and he that watereth are one,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. Was there not a cauſe to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> what they intended, but the liberty of diſſenting was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, and they proceeded to lay aſide their meetings for to conferre together, and to conſider one another, and the <hi>ordinance of the Supper,</hi> that was layd aſide a long time, faſting was perverted to carry on their own deſignes, and to keep the people ignorant of the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and ground of their faſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> being troubled at this, and reſolved not to be <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> to ſee what was done by them, but rather to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, did diſcover my diſlike of theſe practiſes, and bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them to their faces for walking in <hi>craftineſſe,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. and perverting and laying aſide of the <hi>ordinances,</hi> then inſteed of giving me any <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> (as I expected) did they craftily conſpire to <hi>entangle me,</hi> to fall to diſpute about <hi>true Churches.</hi> And to ſeek occaſion againſt me, to defame me, and as if there had not been ſufficient <hi>above ground,</hi> rakt up the <hi>dead</hi> out of her <hi>grave,</hi> and made matter to frame an accuſation againſt me, for doing that which themſelves the generality of them did the ſame, as ſome of them have ſince acknowledged, and in what they accuſed me Mr <hi>Stuckley</hi> himſelfe clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me, and here is the ground of all their charge of <hi>ſcandall,</hi> which how <hi>cruell,</hi> and <hi>unjuſt,</hi> and <hi>unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> it is, I leave to the <hi>impartiall reader</hi> to Judge.</p>
               <p>Thus ſeeing <hi>Goſpell priviledges,</hi> purity of <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> and liberty of <hi>conſcience</hi> lay a bleeding, and they walking contrary to their principles, and often engagements, and having no way to free my ſelfe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170370:60"/>
from partaking with them in their <hi>evils,</hi> not only the liberty of <hi>ſpeaking</hi> but of <hi>diſsenting</hi> being denied, vnles it were purchaſed upon ſuch termes as their <hi>enſnaring</hi> of me, and of looſeing <hi>peace</hi> and a <hi>good name,</hi> I not daring to make it known to other <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> leſt I ſhould be accounted <hi>contentious,</hi> having had experience of the people formerly, and ſeeing the <hi>officers</hi> to be maſters of the ordinance, inſteed of <hi>diſpenſors,</hi> and to <hi>lord it over Gods heritage,</hi> as if they had dominion over our faith: after often ſeeking of the Lord and enquiry in his word according to that light <hi>I</hi> had received, after <hi>I</hi> had declared my <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution</hi> and my grounds to the <hi>elder, I</hi> withdrew, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles rule, 1 <hi>Theſ:</hi> Hoping that by my <hi>withdrawing</hi> they might be more <hi>convinc't,</hi> and that in time the Lord would make them ſenſible of their <hi>uſurpations,</hi> when they ſaw what effects were produced, and ſo might put a ſtop for time to come to ſuch proceedings: and though I could expect little <hi>favour</hi> from them, unleſſe the Lord did convince them, and ſo humble their <hi>Spirits,</hi> yet having the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of mine own <hi>conſcience,</hi> that I could ſay in in ſome meaſure with the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> herein did <hi>I exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe my ſelfe to have alwaies a conſcience void of offence towards God and towards man:</hi> and I conſidered that I ſhould hereby keep and preſerve mine <hi>own peace,</hi> in having no hand in <hi>exalting</hi> of men and ſo opening a way to bring in mens <hi>inventions,</hi> and to worſhip God according to the <hi>precepts of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe in his <hi>Sermon</hi> on that <hi>black</hi> and <hi>dark day</hi> hath acknowledged (as the <hi>Copie</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170370:61"/>
taken from his own mouth will <hi>teſtifie</hi>) that I <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> from them on pretence of <hi>conſcience,</hi> he might have left out the words (on pretence) unleſſe he take upon him to Judge the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> although Mr <hi>Mall</hi> in his printed <hi>True account</hi> (as he cals it) hath not afforded me ſo much <hi>charity</hi> as to put in that perticular.</p>
               <p>And Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> himſelfe afterwards <hi>pag.</hi> 23. ſaith that I went away to avoid the <hi>cenſure;</hi> here he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts himſelfe more waies then one, for 1. If I went away to avoid the <hi>cenſure,</hi> then I could not <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate</hi> on pretence of <hi>conſcience,</hi> but if this be denyed (as the leaving it out of his printed <hi>Sermon</hi> may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre ſo much) 2. If <hi>I</hi> went away to avoid the <hi>cenſure,</hi> then he muſt be forc't to deny that I am <hi>excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated</hi> juſtly for <hi>lying,</hi> for how could I goe away to avoid the <hi>cenſure</hi> for <hi>lying,</hi> afore ever I knew I ſhould be charged with <hi>lying,</hi> for I was never charged by him with <hi>lying</hi> untill ſuch time as I had really with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen and <hi>ſeparated</hi> from them.</p>
               <p>The like Mr <hi>Allen</hi> hath allready declared of his wife, <hi>pag.</hi> 24. of his <hi>Truths manifeſt,</hi> that the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>crime</hi> or <hi>cauſe</hi> of <hi>excommunicating</hi> her, was in time long after ſhe left them.</p>
               <p>Therefore (Reader) take notice of his groſſe <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction</hi> of himſelfe in what he affirmes.</p>
               <p>And whereas he pretends that he had no quiet in his ſpirit that a perſon ſhould lie ſo long <hi>ſuſpended</hi> and give no evidence of <hi>Repentance,</hi> and in his <hi>prayer,</hi> that they have not paſt their <hi>cenſure</hi> in a <hi>revengefull way,</hi> and that they could not anſwer the neglect of their <hi>cenſure</hi> one day longer.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170370:61"/>If it be ſo, why muſt he take liberty to himſelfe to defame me in my name, if it were the <hi>ſinne</hi> only he aymd at? &amp; why did he uſe ſuch <hi>Epithites,</hi> as, <hi>diſconte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lyer, notorious lyer, egregious lyer, Bryer in our ſides, companion for damned ſpirits,</hi> when as his <hi>conſcience</hi> muſt needs tell him, that he never accuſed me of one <hi>lie</hi> all thoſe years that I was in <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with them: And if he found me guilty of a <hi>lye,</hi> let him produce what <hi>lye</hi> it was, I never heard of any yet, whiles I was with them, and when ſince I left them, he carged me at firſt, it was then with an <hi>untruth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although I deſired in our letter ſent them to have the cauſe heard by underſtanding and impartiall men and promiſt to <hi>Submit,</hi> yet he ſlighted that, and hath taken libertie in <hi>pulpit</hi> and in print to render our names and our perſons odious to all the world, as if the <hi>ſword of excommunication</hi> had not been <hi>ſharp</hi> enough, unleſſe it were ſharpned by him at the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins forge,</hi> and in the meane time takes liberty to himſelfe to practice that for which he pretends he hath <hi>cenſured</hi> me as for <hi>lying,</hi> I could inſtance in ſeverall of their <hi>charges</hi> that they are no other but <hi>lies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to mention the ſeverall <hi>reports</hi> that have been ſpread concerning me, as not worth the <hi>taking notice</hi> of, which have one <hi>contradicted</hi> the other, and not two of the <hi>Reporters</hi> found in one <hi>tale,</hi> as hath been taken notice of (as I am informed) by a perſon of credit, this is not worth the <hi>taking notice of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that <hi>falſe report</hi> that hath been raiſed by them and ſpread in citty and countrie on Mr <hi>Ford</hi> the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170370:62"/>
that he ſhould ſlight <hi>lying,</hi> and that ſay lying was the <hi>property</hi> of a woman.</p>
               <p>Whereas the truth is, that when Mr <hi>Ford</hi> and Mr <hi>Bartlet</hi> Miniſters, and Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> and Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> were met at Mr <hi>Fords</hi> houſe, Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> and Mr <hi>Eveleigh</hi> accuſed me of <hi>Scandall,</hi> and brought in a <hi>charge</hi> of <hi>lying</hi> againſt me, inſtancing in Mris <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi> and my ſpeaking againſt the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (which I have allready anſwered) Mr <hi>Ford</hi> ſtill cald for more, more charge: then to make up their <hi>accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they ſaid that I was fickle, Mr <hi>Ford</hi> anſwered them, that is as much as to ſay, ſhe is a woman, this I know to be the truth; and yet the report is ſpread by them in <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> that he ſaid that <hi>lying</hi> was the property of a <hi>woman:</hi> and herein have they diſcovered their falſehood and rage againſt ſuch an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent labourer</hi> in <hi>Chriſts Vineyard,</hi> who hath given abundant <hi>Teſtimony</hi> that he ſeeks not himſelfe but <hi>the things of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Contention,</hi> how hath Mr <hi>Stucley</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered himſelfe guilty to all the world, <hi>Doeg</hi> like, falling on <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> whom he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth ſtands in his way, as his <hi>Sermon</hi> and printed books do witneſſe.</p>
               <p>Give me leave to take notice of it, as <hi>David,</hi> when he heard how <hi>Saul</hi> had cut off the <hi>Lords Prieſts</hi> (ſaith he) I have occaſioned the death of all theſe.</p>
               <p>And for <hi>Cenſoriouſneſſe,</hi> how doth it appeare? not by ſecret ſearch, but upon their ſeverall <hi>Accuſations,</hi> wherein the greateſt ground of their proceedings againſt me, hath been a <hi>cenſuring</hi> of the <hi>ends</hi> of my
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170370:62"/>
words and actions, which is Gods <hi>prerogative</hi> alone, who <hi>ſearcheth the heart, and tryeth the reines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Impartiall Reader</hi> judge whether they ſought the glory of Chriſt, &amp; to convince me of this <hi>ſin,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is that which was &amp; yet is uſually practiſed by themſelves. Witneſſe their uſuall calling Mr <hi>Fords</hi> preaching <hi>Rayling</hi> and <hi>nonſence;</hi> and ſome of them would have the Pulpit ſhut againſt Mr <hi>Ford,</hi> and Would have had the notes of his <hi>Sermons</hi> to pick oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion againſt him, and perſwaded me not to hear him; and I was queſtioned many times for hearing of him, not only the Lords daies, but on Lecture daies alſo.</p>
               <p>I cannot but take notice of Mr <hi>Mall</hi> in his reaſons preſſing them to <hi>renew their Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſaith, ſuch poor wretches are given up to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall hardneſſe,</hi> ſo that they are ſorry for nothing ſo much, as that they with ſuch a <hi>Church</hi> entred into <hi>Covenant</hi> with God; and again, ſuch wrethes they have renewed their <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>hell</hi> and <hi>Satan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For anſwer, what <hi>Covenant</hi> I have ented into with God, whether with them or any other, I deſire ſtill to own and acknowledge, that I am engaged unto to performe, and am reſolved in the <hi>ſtrength of Chriſt</hi> never to retract. And if in any particular I have deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my <hi>Covenant</hi> with God, it lies upon them to <hi>convince</hi> me of it. It is not enough for them to charge <hi>Covenant breaking,</hi> and <hi>perjury,</hi> and <hi>Schiſme:</hi> it lies upon them to prove their charge, otherwiſe I am not engaged to an <hi>Implicite faith</hi> to believe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170370:63"/>I think our letter (we ſent to them) will teſtifie, that we did not retract our <hi>Covenant</hi> with God, when we did profeſſe our <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> to the law and will of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> wherein I think we did own our <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> with God more than they did, who by their <hi>Explicite Covenant</hi> engaged themſelves to an <hi>Impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite faith,</hi> in ſubjection to Mr <hi>Stucley's</hi> miniſteriall guidance and teaching, without any <hi>reſtriction</hi> or <hi>limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> And yet how doth he boaſt pag. 13. as if they were a company of believers that will part from life rather then from a little command, and their hands are fill'd with both <hi>Tables:</hi> is not this practice of theirs a <hi>contradiction</hi> to this profeſſion, &amp; yet pag. 29. exhorting them to keep to the Church of Chriſt, he tells them he cannot but approve of their purpoſe to <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> a <hi>covenant,</hi> that will be a fence againſt a <hi>lawleſſe Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> who was a <hi>ſervant in the houſe of God,</hi> and God teſtifies of him that he was <hi>faithfull in all the houſe of God;</hi> ſee <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.4. <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded us a law, even the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of the <hi>congregation of Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not this fence againſt <hi>lawleſſe Spirits,</hi> that God hath preſcribed his Church ſufficient? but that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley</hi> muſt engage the people to himſelfe, as if his deſigne were to ſeek himſelfe, and to eſpouſe a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to himſelfe, and not to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>It was the <hi>commendation</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gives of his hearers, that <hi>they received the word with all readineſse of mind, and earched the Scriptures dayly, whether thoſe things be ſo or no:</hi> but here they <hi>Ingage</hi> to abſolute <hi>ſubjection</hi> to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucleys</hi> Miniſtry without
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170370:63"/>
any <hi>Caution,</hi> I the rather take notice of it, becauſe they may conſider, that whiles they are <hi>Cenſuring</hi> us, they forget themſelves, and their <hi>Engagements</hi> to Chriſt, and to his Lawes; that whereas they have profeſt the taking Chriſt for their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,</hi> now they ſet up men in the roome of Chriſt, without any mention of the Law and Septer of Chriſt: And yet he pretends that his booke (called <hi>Manifeſt truth</hi>) is ſet forth by him to prevent the <hi>Goſpells ſuffering,</hi> although he ha h had a <hi>Bratherly admonition</hi> given him by the unknowne author, <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trephes detected and Archippus admoniſhed,</hi> yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver takes notice of this particular, to give any <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> unto it, or to remove the <hi>offence</hi> taken by it.</p>
               <p>And now for a cloſe of all I ſhall deſire M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Stucley</hi> to retyre himſelfe a little from the world and thoſe multitudes of <hi>deſignes</hi> hee is at preſent ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with; having done this, ſeriouſly and ſadly conſider a while of that great day of accounts, wherein the <hi>hidden workes of darkneſse</hi> ſhall be fully diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by him whoſe eyes are as a flame of fire: if he doth thinke in good earneſt that there is ſuch a day coming wherein he muſt by <hi>accountable</hi> for all his <hi>actions:</hi> let him I ſay, conſider what <hi>account</hi> he can give to <hi>Chriſt</hi> of his late proceedings againſt Mris <hi>Allen</hi> and my ſelfe; will it (thinks he) be enough to ſay, that his <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> and <hi>eſteem</hi> in the world could not be upheld with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it? that the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of that party with whom he ſided conſiſted therein? that he had <hi>Majors, Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, Knights, Ladies,</hi> to ſtand by him; if he account
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170370:64"/>
theſe vaine and fooliſh pleas, now, why ſhould hee? how dared he act upon ſuch grounds now? His only way therefore will be to repent of this his <hi>wickedneſſe, and pray God, if perhaps the thoughts of his heart may be forgiven him;</hi> which will be more to his <hi>honour,</hi> then by <hi>Printing</hi> any more <hi>angry bookes</hi> againſt two weake <hi>women</hi> (who are not able to ſpeake for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in <hi>Print</hi> (neither is it required) ſo well as men, eſpecially <hi>Schollers</hi>) to <hi>withold the truth in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſse,</hi> to <hi>oppreſſe the Innocent,</hi> and to cover his own <hi>Sin,</hi> which whoſoever doth, ſhall not <hi>proſper,</hi> the mouth of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>ſpoken</hi> it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170370:64"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
